<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Church-lands not to be sold. Or, A necessary and plaine answer to the question of a conscientious Protestant; whether the lands of the bishops, and churches in England and Wales may be sold?</title>
            <author>Warner, John, 1581-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 213 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97178</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W900</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E412_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204017</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863749</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863749</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115963</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97178)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115963)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 65:E412[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Church-lands not to be sold. Or, A necessary and plaine answer to the question of a conscientious Protestant; whether the lands of the bishops, and churches in England and Wales may be sold?</title>
                  <author>Warner, John, 1581-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 81, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1648 [i.e. 1647]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Anonymous; attributed to John Warner.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob: 28"; the "8" in imprint date altered to "7".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church lands --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115963:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CHURCH-LANDS NOT TO BE SOLD. OR, A neceſſary and plaine Anſwer to the Queſtion of a conſcientious PROTESTANT; <hi>Whether the Lands of the</hi> BISHOPS, <hi>and</hi> CHURCHES <hi>in</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Wales <hi>may be ſold?</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 20.25.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>It is a ſnare to the man who devoureth that which is holy.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edward Coke, Inſtit. 2. c. 1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>What ever is granted to Gods Church, <hi>i.e.</hi> to Churchmen, for his honour and maintenance of his Religion and Service, is granted for and to God: and what is given to God, is holy. <hi>Ezek. 48.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 23.10, 11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Remove not the old Land-mark, and enter not into the field of the Fatherleſs, for their Redeemer is mighty, and he ſhall plead their cauſe with thee.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Coke, Ibid.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Our Law-Books teach us, that the Church is ever under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to be under age, and to be as a Pupill or Fatherleſſe: and that it is not agreeable to Law or Right that ſuch ſhould be diſ-inherited.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:115963:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115963:2"/>
            <head>The Heads or Points briefly touched in this Anſwer.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat Lands may be given to the Church, for Gods Service, and Servants therein.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> That Lands ſo given, and accepted, become holy to the Lord.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> That the Lands of Biſhops, and the Churches in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land were ſo given, and therefore may not be aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or ſold.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> That ſuch Alienation, or Selling is forbidden in the Old, and New Teſtament.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> That it hath beene ſo judged by the most ſtrict Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers in the Proteſtant Churches.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> That this kind of Alienation is againſt Prudence, Juſtice, the good of the Kingdome in general, and of the Tenents to ſuch lands in ſpecial.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> That it is againſt the Lawes of this Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> which the two Houſes of Parliament, and
<pb facs="tcp:115963:3"/>Kingdom, by their ſeveral Declarations, Proteſtations, and Covenants, are bound to maintaine.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> That it is againſt the Prudence, and Juſtice of the King; and againſt his lawfull Oath.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> One and twenty Arguments, which are brought in defence of, or colour for ſuch Alienation, are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> The Curſes, and puniſhments, which are ſet downe, and executed in Holy Writ againſt Sacrilegious Alienations, are held forth and opened.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115963:3"/>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> That Lands may be given to the Church, for Gods Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Servants therein.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Id I conceive it proper to this Diſcourſe, and that it would move you, it were eaſie to ſhew out of very good Hiſtories, that the Heathen (who knew not the true God) and Infidels, (not beleeving in our Lord Chriſt) have ſet forth lands and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions for the perpetual maintenance of their Prieſts. I ſhall therefore give you but a touch of this, and that in our owne Land; wherein (then Heatheniſh) were Idol Prieſts,<note place="margin">Antiqu. Brit. Armica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> whom <hi>Lucius</hi> (King in ſome part of Britain) being converted to the knowledge and faith of Chriſt, (about the yeare 176.) rooted out; and <hi>taking away their poſſeſſions and territories, he gave them to the Churches of the beleeving Chriſtians; which he endowed with addition of more lands, and larger immunities.</hi> And that this may not ſeem any new or ſtrange thing, I pray, conſider, that God by his Prophet <hi>Moſes</hi> hath bin pleaſed to expreſſe, that the Egyptian Prieſts had lands; for ſo we read, <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.22. <hi>Onely the lands of the Prieſts he ſold not:</hi> in the margin of which Text it is added, or <hi>of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:</hi> not as doubting whether they were Princes and not Prieſts, but intimating that, as the original word ſignifies both; ſo, they were, or might be, both Prieſts and Princes. And not only the Egyptians, but the Aſſyrians, Chaldeans, Medes, Perſians, Greekes, and Romans, honoured their chiefe Prieſts,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115963:4"/>as Princes:<note place="margin">Baren ad An. <hi>383.</hi>
                  </note> yea, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great being Emperour, and a Chriſtian, yet retained the title of <hi>Pontifex maximous. The great, or high, Priest.</hi> But to returne to our purpoſe, (for we argue not for title, but maintenance) out of that Text of <hi>Gen.</hi> 47. it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares that the people, who were (as the Apoſtle ſpeakes) <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God in the world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.12.</note> yet by the light of natural reaſon, found and held it requiſite, that their Prieſts ſhould have a ſetled maintenance, and that in lands. Give mee leave here to adde what M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Selden,</hi> a man of great reading, hath obſerved, that in ſome parts of Europe, the maintenance of Prieſts lieth wholly in lands. But I muſt to the holy Hiſtorie, and tell you, that ſo ſoone as God had raiſed himſelfe a Church by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of his ſervant <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 7.22.</note> 
                  <hi>(who was learned in all the Wiſdome, Lawes, and Policies of the Egyptians,)</hi> he gave to his ſervants in his Church, beſides 1. <hi>The firſt-borne of all men and ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> 2. Beſides the <hi>firſt fruits of the earth;</hi> 3. Beſides a part in all their ſeverall <hi>Offerings;</hi> 4. Beſides all the <hi>Tithes,</hi> both of their Goods,<note place="margin">Weems Synagog.</note> and of the encreaſe of their Lands: (ſo that if an Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band-man had 6000. buſhels of graine or corne growing in a yeare, after that he had paid all his Tithes, he had left to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe but 4779.) I ſay beſides all this, (though the whole land was hardly 160. miles in length from Dan to Beer-ſheba, and but 46.<note place="margin">Ep. ad Dardan.</note> miles in breadth from Joppa to Bethlehem, (as Saint <hi>Jerome,</hi> who lived long there teſtifieth,) God gave them 18. Cities with the Lands, and Suburbs round about. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Tribe of <hi>Love,</hi> at that time of diviſion of the Land, were but 23000. and the Tribe of <hi>Aſher</hi> was 53000. of <hi>Nepthali,</hi> 45000. of <hi>Zebulun,</hi> 57400. of <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> 64000. of <hi>Dau,</hi> 64000. yet the moſt of the Lands allotted to any of theſe Tribes, exceeded not 19. Cities; ſo bountiful was God under the Law to a corporall abouring Levite, which was but a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of the glorious Sun-ſhine of the Goſpel, and the Royal Prieſt-hood which we enjoy.</p>
               <p>And yet, as though nothing could then under the Law be done too much for the Servants in Gods Temple, King <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> (a Type of Chriſt) not only ſuffered them to enjoy what before had bin given them immediately from God, but, to ſhew the high eſteeme which ought to be had to the Prieſt, whereas
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115963:4"/>the King had a Coine eſtamped with the Sword and Scepter, (which was the Royal Coine,) the Prieſts had their Coine too, bearing the pot of Manna, and <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod, to ſhew it a Royal Prieſt-hood; when as yet (as before is ſaid) it was but a ſhadow of that Royalty, which after appeared under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, whereof Biſhops, and Presbyters, are the Miniſters.</p>
               <p>And ſo long as this honour, and honourable maintenance was continued to the Prieſts, the Church of God, and the whole land flouriſhed, untill the time of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> who by his Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, Idolatry, and Sacrilege, begat that confuſion, which by degrees brought all to utter deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Neither did the Convert Chriſtians, with Judaiſme, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce this kind of Dedicating Lands to God, and his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; for what was that act of the Chriſtians leſſe, which the Apoſtle mentions, <hi>Acts</hi> 4. and 5? Whereupon <hi>Beza,</hi> and other learned Divines hold, that the Chriſtians then and there dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated the lands themſelves, but becauſe the times were ſuch, wherein they lived under the ſpoilers and nobbers of the Church, therefore <hi>they ſold the lands,</hi> and <hi>brought the</hi> whole <hi>price thereof to the Apostles,</hi> (the then Governours of the Church) and ſure it cannot be conceiued in right reaſon, but that thoſe Chriſtians would as willingly and readily have given their lands, which might have continued for a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſtanding maintenance and revenne, as to have ſold the land for money in preſent to be expended.</p>
               <p>And that I give but this one inſtance in the New Teſtament, you will not wonder, when you conſider, 1. that the Church, ſo long as the Apoſtles dived and wrote, was yet in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, but in ſwadling clouts, and under grievous tyranny, and perſecution, and therefore not capable of lands. 2. As yet it had beene improper to have given command or counſel herein, for fenre of a greater perſecution to the Chriſtians: and therefore they left both the advice, and the thing then to be done, when the Church ſhould by Gods mercy obtaine ſome ſettlement; and this was the courſe, which <hi>Moſes</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; who, untill, by vanquiſhing the enemy, he had obtained peace in the Land, ſettled not lands, and a perpetual mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for the Prieſts and Levites in Gods ſervice.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115963:5"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But ſome may happily object, that thoſe lands were not dedicated, or ſold onely for the Apoſtles behoofe and uſe, but for other Chriſtians likewiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>1</label> Which is as readily granted as objected; yet it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, but that all was at the diſpoſe of the Apoſtles, and for ought can be proved to the contrary, at their diſpoſe alone: for wee read that it was <hi>laid downe at the feet of</hi> none but <hi>the Apostles,</hi> and this <hi>laying at the feet,</hi> gives the power of intereſt, and diſpoſe of that which was ſo laid; which might be confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by ſeverall places both in Holy and Prophane Writ. The caſe then I ſuppoſe is cleare, that the Primitive Chriſtians (ſpoken of in the Acts of the Apoſtles) dedicated their lands to God for his ſervants in the Church, which is the joynt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of <hi>Calvin, Beza, Deeda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and other reformed Divines: although by reaſon of the perſecution, they were conſtrained for preſent uſe and neceſſity, to turne thoſe lands into money. 2. It is as cleare that the right, title, or intereſt of that money, being laid at the Apoſtles feet, was in the Apoſtles. 3. That as the money (the price of the lands,) ſo ſhould the lands like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe have beene in the Apoſtles power, if they had been held in kind. 4. From all ſummed up, I conceive it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, but that if in a ſettled time the lands had continued un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſold, the lands themſelves being dedicated to God, the title and intereſt thereof had been in thoſe Apoſtles, who were Gods Vicegerents, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> judiciouſly obſerves on that place.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Which intereſt or title is not a whit diminiſhed by object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that other Chriſtians and Lay-men ſhould have had a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, or benefit by them, as well as by the money; for ſo it is in the lands given to Church men now; who, although they have a title to them in fee, yet they are not to be ſwallowed up whole, or wholly by the poſſeſſours, but to be erogated by the grants, or Lawes of the land, to the reliefe of the poore, for hoſpitality, in pious uſes, and for the behoofe of the King and Kingdome, both in time of peace and warre.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> If nothing hitherto ſatisfie, yet I hope that of our moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour will doe it fully, where he ſaith, <hi>Is it not lawfull for out to doe what I will with mine owne?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.25.</note> Where the Interrogation hath the force of an undoubted affirmation; as if he had ſaid,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115963:5"/>queſtionleſſe, in a juſt, right, lawful way, it is lawful for me, or any man, to doe what I, or hee wil with mine, or his owne; and this I hope comes home to the Propoſition or Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion premiſed, that lands may be given, to the Church for Gods ſervice and ſervants.</p>
               <p>Hitherto I have but barely kept word with you, that wee have from Gods word a Charter, whereby we are enabled to hold lands, if any wil give them; now wil you be pleaſed to conſider whether God in the Old, or Chriſt in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have not given, if not a command, yet a counſell or ſtrong perſwaſion ſo to dedicate or give? That in the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, which ſure hath the power of a Precept, is,<note place="margin">Prov. <hi>3.9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Honour the Lord with thy ſubſtance,</hi> whereby <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> is more eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meant our temporal and worldly ſubſtance, (and why not lands here included?) and by <hi>the Lord,</hi> there is meant the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate honour and maintenance of the Prieſte and Servants of the Lord God.</p>
               <p>And when our Saviour tells it, to the worlds end,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.40.</note> that <hi>what ever good any</hi> Chriſtian, or other <hi>ſhall ſhew to his Apostles and Diſciples, he takes it as done unto himſelfe, and he will reward them;</hi> doth he not herein vehemently perſwade all true Beleevers (at leaſt) to be good and bountifull unto them? And can we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that Chriſt ſtraitened the Chriſtians bounty onely to a competent maintenance, becauſe he there ſpeakes but of feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and cloathing? No ſurely, this were too narrow; it can intend no leſſe then this, that <hi>who ſhall in my name give unto my Diſciples and Apoſtles,</hi> my ſervants and Miniſters preſent, or perpetuall maintenance, in diet, lands, or otherwiſe, hee ſhall not looſe his reward. And if Chriſtians be counſelled or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by Chriſt thus to give to his Apoſtles, Diſciples, and their Succeſſours in his Name, and as for him, ſure it cannot be denied, but that thoſe Apoſtles, Diſciples, and Succeſſours, may receive, and hold ſuch gifts, as in the right of their Lord Chriſt. And that this propoſition (the Miniſters of the Goſpel, may have lands for their maintenance in Gods ſervice,) may be rightly aſſerted from the Old and New Teſtament, I doubt not but to be the opinion of the Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster,</hi> and of all learned Orthodox Divine in Chriſtendome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:115963:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> That Lands ſo given and accepted, become holy to the Lord.</head>
               <p>THe next point is, that lands ſo given for the ſervice and to the ſervants of God, change their common quality or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and are by dedication and Gods acceptation become Gods, and therefore holy: for there are in holy Writ, foure kinds of holy things. 1. Holy manners. 2. Holy meanes leading thereunto; as the holy Word, holy Sacraments, holy Prayer,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.8. <hi>Lev.</hi> 27.9. <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.3.</note> and holy Cenſures. 3. Holy men, as the Prieſt is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Gods holy One: For there is <hi>ſanctitas vitae,</hi> or <hi>converſatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals,</hi> for all men; and <hi>ſanctitas Officii,</hi> or <hi>Functionis,</hi> for the Prieſts. 4. Holy maintenance; all <hi>that any man giveth unto the Lord, ſhall be holy.</hi> And <hi>Lev.</hi> 27.22. <hi>If a man ſanctifie to the Lord a field, which he hath bought,</hi> Ver. 23. <hi>it ſhall be an holy thing unto the Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.25. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 48.15. <hi>V.</hi> 10. <hi>V.</hi> 12.</note> And of ſuch <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>It is a ſnare to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure holy things:</hi> The Prophet <hi>Ezekul</hi> ſpeakes this plainly, And <hi>Lev.</hi> 27.32. the <hi>Tithe</hi> is called <hi>Holy,</hi> the <hi>rest of the land</hi> is termed <hi>a profane place, for the city, for dwelling, and for the ſuburbs:</hi> whereas before, the <hi>oblation of the land</hi> mentioned for <hi>the Prieſts</hi> is called <hi>holy;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 18.1.</note> and <hi>this oblation of that land that is</hi> offered, <hi>ſhall be a thing most holy;</hi> and the Prieſts and Levites maintenance is called <hi>the Lords inheritance:</hi> for then, as now under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, by mans dedication and Gods acceptation, the propriety, as by <hi>Liverie</hi> and <hi>Seiſin</hi> in other lands, is altered and become the Donees, Gods, and therefore is holy; which is plainly and fully confirmed by that of our moſt bleſſed Saviour, in <hi>that ye gave it to my Brethren or Diſciples,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.40.</note> 
                  <hi>ye gave it unto me:</hi> where when they gave, and Chriſt received, it became fully Chriſts; and then and thereby, who will denie it to be holy? The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet tells the Jewes that they had <hi>robbed God;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> the Jewes aske how, <hi>and wherein?</hi> to which Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> expounding the Prophet, ſaith, Ye have robbed me in taking that away which was given to my Prieſts. The Primitive Fathers therefore, call Temples and Churches dedicated to God, (though under the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115963:6"/>names of Saints) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Temples or Houſes of the Lord. And <hi>Optatus</hi> ſaith, <hi>Res est Dei,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ubi Deo aliquid à quocunque oblatum eſt:</hi> And not onely have the Primitive Fathers and Councels ſpoken thus, but both Law and Goſpell prove it; and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> calls <hi>Patrimonium Eccleſiae, Deo conſecratum: (De neceſ. reform. Eccleſiae.)</hi> And <hi>Beza</hi> on <hi>Acts</hi> 5. ſaith, That now under the Goſpel there is a conſecration of things to God is and now what is given to the Church, is given to God. And S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Edward Coke,</hi> (from the moſt ancient learned Sages of the Law) cals Church lands divine Tenements, according to which K. <hi>Ethelred,</hi> long before, <hi>Anno</hi> 998. giving lands to the Church of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> ſtiles them <hi>Patrimonium Christi.</hi> Yea,<note place="margin">Spelm. Conc. p. <hi>506.</hi>
                  </note> the Comment on <hi>Littleton</hi> ſaith, That the King in our Law is <hi>Perſona mixta cum Sacerdote;</hi> and thereby his lands are called and held by our Lawyers to be <hi>Patrimonium ſacrum;</hi> how then can it be denied, that in our Law the Biſhops lands are ſuch?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> That the Lands of Biſhops, and the Churches in <hi>England</hi> were ſo given; and therefore may not be alienated, or ſold.</head>
               <p>ANd that the Lands of Biſhops, and of the Church in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> were ſo dedicated, is eaſie to prove; though firſt I ſhall plainly confeſſe, that as God held not himſelfe tied in the acceptation of lands offered, nor yet the ancient Kings held themſelves bound, when they gave their lands, ſome five, ſome ſix, ſome ſeven, ſome eight, ſome nine hundred yeares agoe, to give them after the manner of a Norman, or a later invented forme of conveyance: ſo indeed can there not be found in the dedication of thoſe lands ſuch formalities as the Lawyers of our time would now require: yet I am confident, that on the Donors part, you ſhall not finde ſo plaine and formal grants of any gifts, or offerings in the Booke of God, (unleſſe you mention thoſe of the Temple) as theſe of the Biſhops lands; and yet thoſe God accepted, took, and held as his. The Tithes and Offerings brought and delivered to the Prieſts and Levites,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115963:7"/>God calls them in divers places <hi>his Inheritance, his Offerings, his Tithes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.1. <hi>Lev.</hi> 27.10. <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.28. <hi>Eze.</hi> 48. <hi>Mel.</hi> 3. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.</note> yet where find we the dedication of them by the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors to God? And the like we may ſay of the Chriſtians dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating and ſelling their lands; yet becauſe the Iſraelites and Chriſtians intended them to God, God ſo accepted them as given to himſelfe; and according, <hi>Marlorat,</hi> the Collector of the Comments of the late Reformed Divines, termes that act of <hi>Ananias, Sacrilega fraudatio, quia ſubduxerat quod ſacrum fuit Deo,</hi> although there is no mention in the dedication there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to God.<note place="margin">Annot. on Act. <hi>5</hi>
                  </note> The Aſſembly of Divines following <hi>Beza,</hi> tranſlate it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to deceive, and ſay that when <hi>Ananias</hi> had dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the poſſeſſion to God for his ſervants, <hi>the fraud concerned Gods intereſt.</hi> So that although much lands heretofore in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> were by the Donors entituled to the Church, to ſuch an Apoſtle or Saint; yet it cannot be denied that they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended and primarily given to the honour of God; and ſo S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Edward Coke</hi> ingenuouſly confeſſes,<note place="margin">Inſtit. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>quod datur Eccleſiae, Dee datur:</hi> and againe, <hi>what is given for God, is given to God.</hi> For who can doubt but he that gives any thing to a ſervant in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the honour and ſervice of the Lord, that hee gives it to the Lord, who wil accept it as a gift to himſelfe?</p>
               <p>But if we ſhal give credit to the beſt Records and Hiſtories, we want not plaine proofes, that much of the lands held by Biſhops and Church-men, were in expreſſe words given to God and Chriſt.<note place="margin">Spelm. Cone. p. <hi>119.</hi> Sumner. p. <hi>47.</hi>
                  </note> About the yeare 605. <hi>Ethelbert</hi> (the firſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King of our Engliſh Nation) giving lands to the Church, ſaith, <hi>Dene, &amp; concedo has terras Deo:</hi> and as hee was the firſt Engliſh Chriſtian King that gave lands to God, ſo was hee the firſt (that I finde) who gave them with this curſe, <hi>Si quis de hac donatione aliquid minuere rentaverit, aut irrirum facere, ſit in praeſenti ſepvratus à ſancta Communione Corporis, &amp; San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinis Chriſti,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 350.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; in die Judicii à conſortio ſanctorum.</hi> K. <hi>Ethelnulph Anno</hi> 855. <hi>dat terras Deo,</hi> (as <hi>Spelman</hi> cites divers Hiſtorians and Records for the proof thereof) and before him K. <hi>Offa Anno</hi> 790. giving lands to the See of <hi>Canterbury,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sum. Appendix of Cant. p. <hi>377.</hi>
                  </note> faith, <hi>Hanc Eleamoſynam offero Deo omnipotenti pro pignore Christianae Fidei:</hi> for which <hi>Sumner</hi> cites the original grant: and K. <hi>Ethelred Anno</hi> 998. confeſſing that by ill counſel he having taken away
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115963:7"/>lands from the Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter</hi> (in <hi>Brumleigh,</hi>) hee now grieved in conſcience for that wicked act,<note place="margin">Regiſt. Roff. f. <hi>8.</hi> B.</note> reſtores them <hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potenti Christo:</hi> I could adde many more the like of the Saxon Kings.</p>
               <p>After whom <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour (in the fourth yeare of his reigne in <hi>England</hi>) chooſeth and ſweareth twelve, the beſt and moſt learned men in the Lawes of the Kingdome, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently to ſearch, and truely to ſet downe the Lawes and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes thereof,<note place="margin">Spelm. Cone. p. <hi>619.</hi>
                  </note> as they were in uſe in the time of K. <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſour: among which Lawes, this is ſet as the firſt, <hi>Omnis Clericus &amp; Scholaris,</hi> (and I hope Biſhops then as now, might and may be underſtood under one of thoſe termes) <hi>&amp; omnes corum poſſeſſiones, ubicunque fuerint, pacem Dei, &amp; ſancta Eccleſiae habeant:</hi> and can any deny, but by the peace of God there is underſtood an immunity from rapine, alienation, or ſelling thoſe poſſeſſions, as belonging to God? A grant of the Conquerour expounds this, wherein he ſaith,<note place="margin">Lamb. Archaiol. f. <hi>125.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Teneant terras &amp; poſſeſſiones ſuas in pace Dei, ab omni exactione injuſtâ libiras.</hi> His ſonne K. <hi>William</hi> the Second, giving lands to the Biſhop of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Regiſt. Roff. f. <hi>11</hi> Ib fol. <hi>13.</hi> Ib. fol. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> ſaith, <hi>Hoc Regium donum facio Deo.</hi> And K. <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt, in his <hi>Inſpeximus</hi> confirmes that grant in the ſame words, K. <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt, <hi>concedit terras pro Deo Eccleſiae Roffenſi:</hi> which is a cleare expoſition of other grants, which runne as many of the Saxon Kings did, <hi>Sancto Petro, Eccleſiae, &amp;c.</hi> K. <hi>John,</hi> as divers other Kings, <hi>dat terras Epiſcopo Roffenſi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ib. p. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp; ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſoribus ſuis, in liberam, puram, &amp; perpetuam Eleemoſynam:</hi> And what is given in Almes, is intended as given to God; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which, the Jewes Corban is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 21.4.</note> 
                  <hi>the offering of God.</hi> And the Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter</hi> pleaded long ſince,<note place="margin">Ib. p. <hi>53.</hi>
                  </note> that he held his lands <hi>in puram Eleemoſynam.</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Edward Coke</hi> (that generally accounted, and ſo by moſt called, Oracle of our Law) ſpeaking of <hi>Frank Almoigne,</hi> or free Almes, ſaith,<note place="margin">Inſtit. <hi>1.</hi> part. p. <hi>94.</hi> B.</note> 
                  <hi>This grant of Frank Almoigne is an ancient grant, and ſhall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed as the Law was, when ſuch grants were made:</hi> and addes, <hi>Our old Law Bookes deſcribe it to be when Lands or Tonements are given to God,</hi> i. e. <hi>ſaith he, to ſuch as are conſecrated for his ſervice:</hi> For ſaith he, <hi>What is done for Gods ſake, is done to God;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 96.</note> and withall cites and allowes of that in the Canon Law, where it
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115963:8"/>ſaith, <hi>Offerings are deſcribed</hi> to be <hi>what ever things are given by Christians to God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Inſtit. <hi>2.</hi> part. p. <hi>489.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and to the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to breake off this long diſcourſe, conſider I pray, in ſtead of all, the great Charter, which ſpeaking of the Rights, Privileges, and Franchiſes of Biſhops and their Churches, ſaith, <hi>Conceſſimus Deo,</hi> we have granted to God, that their Rights, Privileges, Liberties, remaine for ever inviolable; and ſure their lands muſt be compriſed here, for S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Edward Coke</hi> in his Inſtitut. on that Charter, addes, that the <hi>words there, are now to be conſtrued, and that in as large a ſenſe, for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Church, as they were then intended when firſt written:</hi> and by what is before ſpoken, it cannot be doubted that they underſtood the words,<note place="margin">Part. <hi>1.</hi> f. <hi>86.</hi>
                  </note> as of other things, ſo of lands too. Let me adde what I finde in S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Edward Coke, The Biſhop,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Non facit homagium Regi, dicens, ego ſum homo tuns,</hi> doth not homage to the King, ſaying, I am your man; <hi>ſed fidelitatem</hi> (but Fealty) <hi>quia homo eſt ſolius Dei,</hi> becauſe he is the man only of God.<note place="margin">Ib. Sect. <hi>133.</hi>
                  </note> And then <hi>what is given to the man of God, in our Law is given to God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> That ſuch Alienation or Selling, is forbidden in the Old and New Teſtament.</head>
               <p>NOw me thinkes that which hath hitherto been ſaid, might terrifie any profeſſour of Gods truth, from the ſelling, buying, or alienating ſuch lands ſo given; but, becauſe nothing but expreſſe words in Scripture wil now a dayes ſerve the turn, (and would to God that might ſerve) I pray conſider the word of God by his Prophet,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 48.14.</note> expreſly ſaying, <hi>Ye ſhall not ſell, nor exchange, nor alienate, what is offered to the Lord.</hi> Where God, to ſtop the mouth of all cavillers, doth, as our Lawyers, put in words enough; Yee ſhall not <hi>ſell,</hi> nor <hi>exchange,</hi> nor <hi>alienate.</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> Where if any will prove ſo wittie againſt God and his Word, as to ſay, the Prophet there ſpeaks not of Lands, but of Tithes and Offerings, which were not to be ſold, becauſe that were
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115963:8"/>againſt the Law eſtabliſhed by God: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> Yet marke I pray, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be not a cavill; for the force of Gods prohibition lies not in this, that they were Tithes; nor in this, becauſe he had forbidden them to be ſold; but becauſe they were offered to the Lord: for ſo the Text ſpeakes, <hi>Ye ſhall not ſel, nor exchange, nor alienate, for it is holy to the Lord,</hi> and ſo were become his; and ſuch (as I have proved) were the lands of Biſhops in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and the ſame being the ground and reaſon of the prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition now, as then, becauſe offered, given, or <hi>holy to the Lord,</hi> I cannot ſee but the prohibition hath the ſame force againſt ſelling lands given to God under the Goſpel, as it had under the Law.</p>
               <p>And, if we well weigh the puniſhment of <hi>Ananias</hi> and his wife, it will appear that in Gods judgement,<note place="margin">Act. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> the prohibition ſhould hold more ſtrong under the Goſpel, then it did under the Law; for there <hi>Ananias</hi> but intended, or promiſed his lands, or price thereof to the Church; and they were <hi>his own,</hi> and ſo much his own, that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> tells him,<note place="margin">V. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> that is <hi>was in his power, not</hi> to have promiſed them: and yet for deteining but a part of this ſo lately <hi>his own,</hi> hee is ſuddenly ſtrooke dead, and for ought we know without repentance. Believeſt thou the Scriptures? Then believe and know God will not be mocked with cavils, or Law-termes, or diſtinctions; but, as he is a God that knoweth the heart, and ſearcheth the reins, ſo where he findes Chriſtians, as <hi>Ananias,</hi> to goe about to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive or cheate him, he will finde this man out, and though he ſtrike him not ſuddenly dead, yet ſhall <hi>Gods wrath come like water into his bowels, and like oyle into his bones, or it ſhall be as a fire to conſume his houſe.</hi> But I feare too many there be, who, as they denie all relative holineſſe to the Churches, the utenſils, and the Miniſters of God under the Goſpel; ſo upon the point, they would that an <hi>Index expurgatorius</hi> ſhould paſs upon all Sacrilege, as though under the Goſpel, there were now no ſuch ſinne: for to profane Gods Houſe and Ornaments, is with them no Sacrilege; to contemne and abuſe Gods Miniſters, is (as Chriſt propheſied) in their account, to <hi>doe God ſervice,</hi> and no Sacrilege. Yea, it is almoſt publiſhed, that it is no Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege to deteine, or utterly to take away the maintenance of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115963:9"/>Miniſters, which are Tithes; and yet if we beleeve Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> there is ſuch a ſinne now, which if it be not materially in the Houſes, the Tithes or the Miniſters of God, then ſure it muſt be in the patrimony of the Church:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.22.</note> for Saint <hi>Paul</hi> fights not with the aire, neither reproves or forbids he that which is not ſinne.</p>
               <p>And it will appeare, that the Sacrilegious perſon in aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Church lands, breaks two Commandements in the firſt Table, &amp; two in the ſecond. The ſixt Precept, ſaying, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exed. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> is not bounded alone in depriving a man of his life, but in taking away his livelihood, the maintenance of life. <hi>Whoſe robbeth his father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.24.</note> (God,) <hi>his mother,</hi> (the Church) <hi>homicidae par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticeps, is a companion</hi> (ſo our Bible) in ſin, and ſentence with <hi>the deſtroyer;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal</hi> 74.10. <hi>de Leg.</hi> 10.</note> and this kil-man, is ſaid to blaſpheme God too, and therein to breake the third Commandement. <hi>Plate</hi> ſpeaks it, who dares doe this, ſaith (in his heart at leaſt) either there is no God, or which is all one, thinks him not juſt, or not omnipotent, and therefore, <hi>per ſe,</hi> as actor, <hi>per aliot,</hi> as author, blaſphemeth God.<note place="margin">D. Fulk Aretix. in Act. <hi>5</hi>
                  </note> Yea, ſome late Divines, of no meane rank, ſticke not to ſay, that <hi>Ananias</hi> committed the ſinne, not to be prayed for, againſt the Holy Ghoſt, and therefore was ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtrooke dead without repentance. But holy Writ wil directly indict the Sacrilegious perſon for breach of the eighth and of the ſecond Precept: to the firſt, this alienating and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Gods, and the Churches lands, is the ſinne, which by the Primitive and beſt reformed Divines,<note place="margin">Diodat. in Act. <hi>5</hi>
                  </note> is called Sacrilege. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conſecration, the thing is no more thine but Gods, and in taking or detaining it, thou haſt committed Sacriledge: which in Scripture language,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.25. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 48.14. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.22. <hi>Act.</hi> 19.37.</note> 
                  <hi>is expreſt by <hi>devouring:</hi> in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> by ſelling, exchanging, alienating:</hi> in <hi>Malachi,</hi> by <hi>robbing God:</hi> in Saint <hi>Paul</hi> by <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which from the derivation of the word, is to ſteale that which is holy: and ſo we tranſlate <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Church-robbers;</hi> by all, if not by every of which Texts, it is plain, that to alienate, or ſell, lands or goods of the Church, is a ſinne againſt the eighth Commandement, which forbids all manner of taking away that from any other, which is his, and not thine.</p>
               <p>Some learned, not onely ancient, but moderne Divines goe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115963:9"/>further, &amp; ſay that it is Sacrilege to invert or turn thoſe things to other uſes, which were primarily dedicated to God and his ſervice; and thus much M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> plainly affirms, ſaying, It is Sacrilege, <hi>facultates Eccleſiae in alienos uſus convertere:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tract. De neceſ. reform. Eccleſ. Aunot. in Prov. <hi>20.25.</hi>
                  </note> to imploy the revenues or goods of the Church to any other uſes, then for the Church. And the Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> ſay, That <hi>to take that which was appointed to Gods uſe, yea to goe about to do it by enquiring how the Vow may be avoided,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">On Mal. <hi>3.8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>is to devoure holy things.</hi> And they ſay, <hi>No Heathen is ſo barbarous, as to defraud his God, and to deale deceitfully with him:</hi> And they adde, <hi>To keepe thoſe things backe, which belong to God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">On Ver. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and are to furniſh out his ſervice, and for the maintenance of his Officers, is to rob God.</hi> Some ancient,<note place="margin">S. Chryſ. M. Calo.</note> and later choice Divines have thought that the words of Saint <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 2.22. were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of ſome convert Jewes, new Chriſtians, who thought they might without offence, robb and ſpoil the Temples of the Idols; and yet the Apoſtle condemnes this as a ſinne in them, ſaying, <hi>Thou that abhorrest Idols, committest thou Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege?</hi> Which if it hold ſo, then how much more ſurmounts the Sacrilege of our times that of the firſt convert Chriſtians? When as we ſticke not to nick-name it to be pure Religion, when we take away, or ſpoil that which was offered to the true God, and his Servants. And may I not here take up the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>O thou that abhorrest Idols!</hi> Yea, the very ſhadow and word Idolatry, art thou become ſo abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable in thy hypocriſie, as to robb thy God? and yet would'ſt be held a Reformed Proteſtarit, and lover of God? Be not deceived, if Saint <hi>Paul</hi> judge right, (which none doubts but an infidel) thou art a thiefe and a robber. And I could wiſh that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> from this Text, could doom thee no further then a thiefe, and tranſgreſſour of the ſecond Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; for I feare upon a review of the Text, it will be found, that thou haſt ſinned againſt the firſt Table too. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> affirmaes it directly, which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Zanchie,</hi> the beſt Reformed Schoole Divine ſhewes thus; He grubs up the root, the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which gives life to the branches, the Miniſters; which failing, the fruit, Gods honour, muſt needs fall to the ground. But without ſtraying from the Text, obſerve Saint <hi>Paul,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115963:10"/>Thou that preacheſt a man ſhould not steale. doſt thou ſteale?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ver.</hi> 21, 22.</note> And <hi>thou that ſayeſt a man ſhould not commit adultery, doſt thou commit adultery?</hi> In both which, the ſinnes are of the ſame nature, and againſt the ſame Precept: as <hi>ſtealing, and ſtealing; adultery, and adultery;</hi> and preſently he ſubjoynes, <hi>Thou that abhorreſt Idols, commateſt thou Sacrilege?</hi> Which ſhewes, that as the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, ſo theſe are the breach of the ſame Commandement. And ſo M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> upon the place ſaith, <hi>The Apoſtle here oppoſeth Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege to Idolatry, as a ſinne of the ſame kind:</hi> and rightly ſo, for as God, where he forbids the worſhip of Idols, there hee forbids the offering, or giving lands, or goods to them, or to their Prieſts: ſo, when he commands to worſhip God, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to add what we may, but in no ſort to take away what is given or offered for his Honour or Service: for this is a breach of his divine Precept in the firſt Table. And I cannot readily ſay, whether or no Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in this comparative ſpeech, <hi>Thou that abhorreſt Idols, committeſt thou Sacrilege?</hi> makes not Sacrilege a greater ſinne then Idolatry; for, before in the two former comparates, he reaſons from the leſſer ſin to the greater; as, <hi>Thou that preacheſt a man ſhould not ſteale, or commit adultery,</hi> which are ſinnes in another man, doſt thou commit thoſe things, which muſt needs be a greater ſinne in thee, who acteſt what thou preacheſt againſt, and condemneſt? And ſo, <hi>thou that abhorreſt Idols,</hi> doſt thou robb God of that which is given to his Honour and Service, which muſt needs be a greater ſinne in thee? For, if to give God more worſhip then he requires, or otherwiſe then he commands, (though it be done with a good intention) be Idolatry, (as Reformed Divines ſay) why then may it not reaſonably be conceived to be a greater ſinne, utterly to take away that from him which is given for his Honour, then to give him ſome more Honour then he requireth? But I leave the determination of this point to the Aſſembly of Divines,<note place="margin">Annot. on Rom. <hi>2.22.</hi>
                  </note> who upon the words, move the Queſtion, <hi>Why the Apostle changeth the word? And whereas he ſaid before, ſteale, and ſteale, commit adultery, and commit adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery; Why,</hi> ſay they, <hi>doth he vary and ſay, Why thou that abhorreſt Idols, committeſt thou Sacrilege?</hi> To which Queſtion, they, in their Notes, thus anſwer: <hi>The Apoſtle uſeth have an aggravation,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115963:10"/>as if he ſhould ſay, Thou that abhorreſt Idoſe, doſt thou commit a worſe ſinne? to wit, Sacrilege, which robbeth God of his Honour?</hi> Thus they. Let me add, that it is a ſinne, not againſt the poſitive written Law alone, but againſt the very Law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; for ſo the Prophet argues, <hi>Will a man?</hi> any man?<note place="margin">Mal. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> any Pagan, Heathen, natural man? will he <hi>robb his God? i. e.</hi> He will not; for it is againſt the Law of nature. How great then is this ſinne in a Chriſtian, who hath not onely the Moral Law of Nature, and the poſitive Moral written Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but the Law of grace to reſtraine him?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> That it hath been ſo judged by the moſt ſtrict Reformers in the Proteſtant Churches.</head>
               <p>IT were eaſie to give you the ſayings of many Primitive Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Fathers in this caſe; but conceiving that the later Divines reliſh better with you, I ſhall therefore ſet downe the judgement of the three Oracles, (as they are held by many) of the firſt, beſt, and ſtricteſt Reformed Churches, in <hi>Germany, France,</hi> and <hi>Scotland:</hi> And for <hi>Germany,</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Luther,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">On Gal. <hi>6.6.</hi>
                  </note> when hee ſaw the Clergy deſpiſed, and their lands taken away, Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Printed theſe words; [The Apoſtle] <hi>here cloſely touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the manners of our Countrey-men, who moſt ſecurely contemne our Ministery; and eſpecially the Nobles, who make their Paſters, as their baſe and obnoxious ſervants; in ſo much, that if we had not ſo godly a Prince, (as God be thanked we have) and ſo great a lover of the truth, they had, ere now, driven us out of the land; and yet theſe would be accounted Goſpellers.</hi> After this, he meets with a tacit Objection: <hi>viz.</hi> That theſe Revenues of the Church were given in the time of Popery; to which he anſwers in theſe words, <hi>Gram it that theſe goods were, by moore imposture, heaped up for Papiſts, yet God, ſpoyling the Egyptians,</hi> i. e. <hi>Papiſts, of their goods, tranſtated them to good uſes in our Land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He goes on, <hi>The Devill hath but two ordinary wayes to deſtrey Religion, the one is by the errors of Hereticks,</hi> (againſt which we
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115963:11"/>had by Ordinance a day of Humiliation,)<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t.</hi> 10. 1646.</note> 
                  <hi>the other by depriving of Gods Ministers of their Rights; and this ſaith he, is the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils maſter-piece, hereby to destroy Religion, without either the force of Tyrants, or the ſubtle worke of Hereticks. But know</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that although God for a time defers to puniſh, yet in his own time he will finde you out, and plague your dog-like ſcorne and hate to Gods Miniſters:</hi> For ſaith he, <hi>The higheſt of the Gentry, and moſt covetous of the City, and the baſeſt in the Countrey, when they draw neere to death, ſhall finde that God will not be mocked: but as they have ſowne, ſo ſhall they reap for ever.</hi> Thus farre the firſt great publike Reformer of the Proteſtants Church in <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next to him,<note place="margin">De neceſ. reform. Eccleſ.</note> heare M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> thus ſpeaking; I profeſſe, ſaith he, that I am much diſpleaſed that the Revenues of the Church are not imployed for thoſe uſes alone, for which they were dedicated: and that it is not ſo, I and all good men hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily grieve. For, ſaith he, it is an inexpiable Sacrilege to take the patrimony of the Church, and to waſt the ſame on pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane uſes: and what hee meanes by profane uſes and waſting, he explaines in theſe words, when he ſaith, I aſſent to this as a truth, that it is <hi>Sacrilege to convert or change the goods or revenues of the Church to any other uſe, then for the Church:</hi> And adds, <hi>Seldome have I found but that ſuch Alienations of Church lands, have drawne ſome miſchiefe after them:</hi> and hee not onely determines this kind of Sacriledge to be ſuch a grievous ſinne and dangerous to the State, but even to the perſons plotting and acting in the ſame; for ſo he concludes, <hi>I confeſſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that in Scripture grievous puniſhments are pronounced againſt ſuch men, as ſhall ſpoile the Church of her goods and Revenues.</hi> And when you ſhall conſider that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> wrote this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe to the Emperour and Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> aſſembled at that time in a Diet (or Parliament) for the Reformation of the Church; then well weigh how at this time, his judgement and ſentence ſhould prevaile with you in this caſe, who, for holineſſe, learning, and judgement, is ſo extolled by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Churches. Will you heare but one paſſage for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Beza</hi> ſucceſſour to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> in <hi>Geneva,</hi> and it ſhall be that which hee wrote in his anſwer to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Saravia?</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115963:11"/>who touching upon the diſſolution, and paſſing away the Lands of the Religious Houſes in the time of K. <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, ſaith, <hi>We and all good men heartily bewaile that ſcattering of the Church Lands, accompanied with a moſt wicked, and deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sacrilege.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And from <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> let us to our Poleſtarre in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and here Mr <hi>Knox</hi> the prime principal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former of that Kirk, who, with his brethren Miniſters,<note place="margin">In Book of Diſc. <hi>1560.</hi>
                  </note> deſires the Lords of the Councel, for <hi>feare of the loſſe of their ſoules, to make reſtitution of the Lands of the Church, and of the Friers:</hi> and in his Letter on his death-bed,<note place="margin">In the yeare, <hi>1572.</hi>
                  </note> he commands his Brethren to <hi>withſtand the devourers of the Church Patrimony, wherein if they</hi> (the devourers) <hi>ſhall perſist, yet communicate ye not with them by conſent, or by ſilence.</hi> And in the Booke of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline,<note place="margin">1569.</note> 
                  <hi>The Patrimony of the Church is declared to be all things doted to the Church:</hi> and it pronounces <hi>them to be theeves, who have taken them from the Church;</hi> and affirmes,<note place="margin">In ſecond Book of Policy, c. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>to take away any thing which was given to the Church, to be deteſtable Sacrilege before God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, the whole Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> in their Aſſembly, enjoynes a publike Faſt throughout all the whole Kingdome,<note place="margin">At Edenburgh, <hi>1582.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>To appeaſe Gods wrathon the Land, for that crying ſinne of Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege therein committed.</hi> Now can any, who have ſworne to maintaine the Doctrine and Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> know this, and yet Vote the ſelling of Church Lands? If ſo, why may we not pray, <hi>Lord have mercy on them?</hi> For did ever any Proteſtant Church maintaine, that Church lands might be taken or ſold from the Church? If not, (which I perſwade my ſelfe they have not) then why doe you not feare that you are not in the right way, or not right <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> but rather in this point, that you are <hi>Papiſts?</hi> For that theſe onely of all Chriſtian Churches have allowed the practice of it? and yet theſe doe it not but under the colourable and falſly preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded power, which the <hi>Pope</hi> uſurps, as being Chriſts Vicar on earth; Whereby, he ſaith, he may diſpenſe with the Church lands as he pleaſeth: which title or power, I hope our Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth not aſſume or challenge to themſelves, although K. <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth in the diſſolution of the Abbies, thus ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115963:12"/>If the Pope and his Legate the Cardinal doe it, then why not I? And yet I pray note by the way, that K. <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, ſo decryed for a notorious Sacrilegiſt, yet never did he take away the lands of Biſhops, nor Cathedrals: but on the contrary, he founded ſome, and enlarged others. But why in Gods name are not the Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> conſulted with in this point? Or why doe not our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Brethren read the Annotations of the Aſſembly, who note, <hi>that Egypt</hi> (which would not in the greateſt extremity of famine,<note place="margin">On Gen. <hi>47.</hi>
                  </note> when all other mens lands were ſold, yet then that they would not ſell the lands of the Prieſts) <hi>ſhall riſe up in judgement againſt the alienators or ſellors of lands, which have been dedicated to God or his Servants.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> That this kind of Alienation, is againſt Prudence, Justice, the good of the Kingdom in general, and of the Tenents to ſuch Lands in ſpecial.</head>
               <p>BUt were there not ſo much ſaid in Gods Book, and by learned Orthodox Divines, ſhall neither our owne Lawes, nor <hi>Prudence,</hi> nor <hi>Juſtice</hi> prevaile in this caſe, to keep us from ſelling of Church Lands? For what <hi>Juſtice</hi> is it to ſell that, which is not our owne? And that theſe lands are 1. Gods, I hope it is proved ſufficiently by Gods words, the verdict of allowed Divines, and ſhall be further proved anon by the Lawes of our Land. 2. They are the Biſhops, who are Gods Aſſignes and Uſufructuaries; and theſe lands are theirs by as good title in Law, as any man can hold any land in this Kingdome. 3. They are by Patronage, the Kings; for this is very lately profeſſed in a good Parliament,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Jacob.</hi> 3.3</note> in theſe words, <hi>Whereas all the Lands of the Biſhops in</hi> England, <hi>and Dominion of</hi> Wales, <hi>were given by Kings of</hi> England, (the full truth where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I will not diſpute) <hi>whereby the King is become the lawfull and rightfull Patron of all thoſe Lands;</hi> therefore it is deſired <hi>that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115963:12"/>the King would enact.</hi> (not that they without the King would or could, no ſuch power then knowne) and what is deſired? not that the <hi>Biſhops Lands</hi> ſhould be ſold, but that they <hi>may not be leaſed out by the Biſhops, for longer terms of time, then for</hi> 21. <hi>yeares, or three lives, no not to the Crowne?</hi> And is this <hi>Justice</hi> ſo ſoone forgotten, or ſo ſoone changed, in ſo ſhort a time, that without the conſent of <hi>God the Proprietary,</hi> of the <hi>King the Patron,</hi> and of the <hi>Biſhops the Aſſignes,</hi> the lands ſhall be utterly ſold away? And yet muſt we call this <hi>Juſtice?</hi> I pray God this <hi>Juſtice</hi> call not for judgement from heaven.</p>
               <p>And whether it can be <hi>juſt</hi> to ſell the <hi>Biſhops Lands,</hi> I pray, examine by that rule and touch-ſtone of true Moral <hi>Juſtice,</hi> which our Lord Chriſt hath expreſſed in two ſhort Precepts; the one, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelfe:</hi> The other,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Whatſoever ye would that men ſhould doe unto you, doe you even ſo unto them, for this is the Law and the Prophets.</hi> Now by the firſt rule, examine your ſelves, whether in this act of ſelling the <hi>Biſhops Lands,</hi> you love the <hi>Biſhops</hi> as your ſelves? And trie this by the other, whether you would yeeld your conſent, as to a thing juſt, that if the <hi>Biſhops</hi> had your power, they might and ſhould preſerve to themſelves their own lands and expoſe yours to ſale? If your hearts ſpeake the truth, I feare they would denie this to be juſt in the <hi>Biſhops</hi> againſt you: and if ſo, then be aſſured, that in this act of ſelling the <hi>Biſhops lands,</hi> you doe not that, which by the verdict of your owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, is juſt. And if you will (as Law-makers ſhould) look forward, and provide for future times; ſtands it with civil <hi>Prudence</hi> to ſell thoſe Lands away, which doe and will yeeld ſo much for maintenance of the King and Kingdome, in Tenths, Firſt-fruits, Subſidies and Taxes, which for the moſt part will bee ſwallowed up, when fallen into Lay-hands? 2. Stands it with civil <hi>Prudence</hi> to robb Tenents of ſo good penniworths, as they now hold from <hi>Biſhops</hi> and Church-men; which they muſt not expect, when in Lay-hands, whereby they have beene enabled the better to ſerve the King and Kingdome in time of need? 3. Stands it with <hi>Prudence</hi> and <hi>Charitr,</hi> to caſt ſo many into a ſtate of beggery, and danger of theeving, who by <hi>Biſhops</hi> and Church-men have been reaſonably relieved
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115963:13"/>by under Offices, and places in the Church? Upon the diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the Religious Houſes, in the Reign of K. <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth,<note place="margin">Chron. f. <hi>773.</hi>
                  </note> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Speed</hi> ſaith, that a great Rebellion was raiſed in <hi>Lincolnſhire;</hi> and the Rebels expreſſing the cauſe thereof to the King, they ſay, <hi>Wee grieve for the ſuppreſſion of ſo many Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Houſes, whereby the Pooralty of your Realme is unrelieved, and many put off their livings, which is a dammage to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</hi> Soone after another Rebellion aroſe in <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> where 40000. with Horſe, Armes, and Artillery, roſe for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, who had upon their ſleeves the Name of the Lord; the ground of their riſing was (ſaith the ſame Author) <hi>That the King by his evill Counſellers, will deſtroy the Ministers of the Church,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>f.</hi> 775.</note> 
                  <hi>which makes against the Common good.</hi> 4. Stands it with a Religious, and civil <hi>Prudence</hi> to robb Learning and Religion of that profit and preferment, which encouraged the ſtudy and encreaſe both of Learning and Religion?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Where no oxen are, the crib is cleane:</hi> And the Land, ſoon after K. <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> found this true:<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 13.33.</note> for, when <hi>Jeroboam</hi> had taken away the beſt maintenance of the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> what followed? but that the <hi>Prieſts</hi> were choſen out of the <hi>lowest of the people?</hi> (Which I would it were not too true now in our Land,) and in after times, the Church ſuffered more under <hi>Julian,</hi> then <hi>Diocleſian:</hi> for this tooke away the able men; but that Apoſtate their maintenance. I ſhall cloſe this point with that memorable paſſage of S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Edward Coke</hi> in <hi>Wincheſters</hi> Caſe, <hi>The decay of the Revenues of the Church, will draw after it the downe-fall of Gods Service and Religion:</hi> which God in mercy avert.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> That it is againſt the Lawes of this Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> which the two Houſes of Parliament, and Kingdome, by their ſeverall Declarations, Proteſtations, and Covenants, are bound to maintaine.</head>
               <p>BUt if neither Gods Word, nor the Verdict of beſt Divines, nor <hi>Juſtice,</hi> nor <hi>Prudence,</hi> can be heard; yet I pray heare
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115963:13"/>what our <hi>Lawes</hi> ſay in this caſe; and yet before I urge theſe, (to which I am as much a ſtranger as to the Profeſſion) let me remember you with that, which I have heard to be a Maxime in our Law, <hi>That no Statute, Law, or Cuſtome, which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods Law, or Principles of Nature, can be of any validity, but are all null:</hi> which if granted, it will ſave me the paines to cite our Lawes, as having before proved, that it is againſt Gods Law, to ſell away the lands of <hi>Biſhops.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet let me adde, that one Statute ſaith,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> That <hi>the King by evil Counſellors, cauſed the Temporalties of Biſhops to be ſeized in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his hands, for a time, to the great dammage of the ſaid Biſhops, which from henceforth ſhall not be done:</hi> and this Statute is not repealed, and therefore is in its full force at this day, as all other Statutes unrepealed are.</p>
               <p>I might add another Statute,<note place="margin">17 <hi>Edw.</hi> 2.</note> that when the <hi>Templars</hi> (theeving, bloudy, decried Souldiers) had their Lands taken from them; yet were not thoſe lands then divided among <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament men,</hi> nor ſold for the Common-wealth, (although the Kingdome at that time was in diſtreſſe and want enough, I beleeve more then now) no, the then <hi>Parliament,</hi> ſurely, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, they might doe neither of theſe; they therefore tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thoſe lands, and ſettled them on the Priorie of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>John</hi> of Jeruſalem: and in the ſame Statute it is inſerted, that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then did not alienate the Lands of thoſe Templars: 1. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were given to God, though poſſeſſed by men.</hi> 2. <hi>Becauſe they held it a ſinne to rob the Donors of their gift.</hi> 3. <hi>Becauſe they held it would prove mortal to the Alienators:</hi> and theſe cauſes were then held ſufficient to keep a Parliament from ſelling or alienating Church Lands. And it is in the ſame Statute provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that if in after times, the ſaid Hoſpitalers, or their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, ſhall be put out of any of thoſe lands, they ſhall have power to recover the ſame according to the Law of the Realm.</p>
               <p>I have likewiſe read, that in the 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. it is declared,<note place="margin">In the Review of the Covenant, Printed <hi>1644.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>That Lay-men have no authority to diſpoſe of the Lands or Goods of the Church, for they are only committed to the Prieſts to be diſpoſed of.</hi> I confeſſe, I finde it not in the printed Statutes; but this I find and read there, <hi>That none, high nor low, by any occaſion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3 <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall courſe in any Parke, nor fiſh in any Pond of a Prelate, or other
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115963:14"/>Religious perſon, without the leave or will of the Lord, or of his Bayliffe.</hi> In thoſe times, ſure the Parliaments found not that they had power to ſell away the Biſhops Lands; and I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that the Parliament deemed not then, that they had any ſuch power, by reaſon of the <hi>great Charter,</hi> granted by this Kings father, (which Charter S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Edward Coke</hi> calls <hi>the Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke of the Subjects Tenures in England,</hi>) and therefore upon this, give me leave a little longer to inſiſt, as being a maine part, and foundation of our Lawes.</p>
               <p>One Statute enacts,<note place="margin">42 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> That <hi>if any Statute be made contrary to the great Charter, it ſhall be void;</hi> which Statute is ſtill in force: and now heare, what this Charter ſpeakes concerning the Lands of the Church, and of Biſhops, and then ſay truely, whether it be not againſt the Law of <hi>England,</hi> to ſell theſe Lands. In this Charter (confirmed two and thirty times by our beſt Parliaments) it is expreſly ſaid, <hi>Wee have granted to God, and by this our Charter have confirmed for us, and our heires for ever, that the Church of</hi> England <hi>ſhall be free, and ſhall have all her whole Rights,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2</hi> part Inſtitut. in Procemio.</note> 
                  <hi>and Liberties inviolable. The great Charter,</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edward Coke, <hi>is no new Law, but it is declaratory of the principal fundamental Lawes of</hi> England.<note place="margin">25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1.</note> And he ſaith, The <hi>Nobles and great Officers were to be ſworn to the obſervation of it: and by a Parliament, it was judged to be taken as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law of</hi> England: and well may, conſidering the four cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes or ends of that Charter, as is expreſt in the entrance: <hi>viz.</hi> 1. The honour of God. 2. The health of the Kings ſoul. 3. The advancement of the Church. 4. The amendment of the Kingdome.</p>
               <p>And now heare this Law ſpeake (which is almoſt the ſame which was granted by K. <hi>John</hi> in the nineteenth yeare of his Reign) with the interpretation of the Oracle of our Law;<note place="margin">Pariſ. p. <hi>255.</hi> Sir Edward Coke on the Charter.</note> and firſt (as all beſt Grants have) it begins with God, and ſaith, <hi>Conceſſimus Deo;</hi> where the Interpreter ſaith, What is given to the Church (as Biſhops lands were) is given to God: and what hath this Law granted to God? Why, <hi>that the Church ſhall be free:</hi> where the Interpreter tells you, that <hi>by the Church is meant all Eccleſiaſtical perſons, their poſſeſſions and goods:</hi> And theſe ſhall be free, ſaith he, from all exactions and oppreſſions.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115963:14"/>and to ſell away their lands, is it neither oppreſſion nor exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? If not, heare the Charter and Interpreter goe on. Wee have granted to God that the Church ſhall have <hi>all her Rights entire, i.e.</hi> ſaith the Interpreter, That all Eccleſiaſtical per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhall enjoy all their Rights wholly, without diminution or ſubſtraction whatſoever: Whereby, ſaith hee, all their Rights are confirmed, <hi>as they had them before, or as at the firſt grant;</hi> and then they had them not to be ſold. It goes on, and that the Church, or Church-men have, and <hi>hold all their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties;</hi> Which liberties, ſaith he, grants them the liberty of the Law of <hi>England,</hi> the Privilege of Parliaments, and all Grants by Charter or Preſcription: and ſhall none of theſe keep the Biſhops Lands from ſale? Moreover theſe Grants are not alone for that, or any ſet time, but for ever; Heare the Charter, <hi>This we have granted to the Church, i.e.</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, for our ſelves, and our heires <hi>for ever:</hi> Which, ſaith the Interpreter, is added, to take away all ſcruple, that this Charter or Grant ſhould live, and take effect for ever. And which is not unworthy your obſervation,<note place="margin">12 <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 23.</note> in our printed Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, there is an heavy Curſe denounced againſt all thoſe, who ſhall breake this great Charter.</p>
               <p>And now if you grant (which I think you will not denie) that this Charter is a part of our Law, then I hope, it will follow, that by our Law, the Lands of the Church or of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, may not be ſold or alienated.</p>
               <p>You have ſeene what the Charter hath granted the Biſhops, as Church-men;<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> now conſider what the ſame Charter grants them as free-borne Subjects of the Kingdome: <hi>Nullus liber homo,</hi> ſaith it, <hi>capiatur, vel impriſonetur, vel diſſeiſiatur de li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bero Tenemento ſuo, vel libertatibus, vel liberis conſuetudinibus ſuis, niſi per legale judicium parium ſuorum, vel per legem terrae.</hi> Where the Interpreter expounds, 1. Who is a free-man: 2. What diſſeiſing is: 3. What is the Law of the Land. To the firſt he ſaith, That every <hi>free-born Subject</hi> is meant here to be a free-man. To the ſecond, to be <hi>diſſeiſed,</hi> ſaith he, is to be put out of his ſeiſin, or diſpoſſeſſed of his free-hold, that is, lands or livelihood. To the third, by the <hi>Law of the Land,</hi> ſaith he, that is, either by the Common Law, or the Statute
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115963:15"/>Law, or the Cuſtome of <hi>England.</hi> And for further explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion adds, by the <hi>Law of the Land,</hi> is underſtood by proceſſe of Law, by indictment or preſentment of good and lawful men: And all this, ſaith he, is no new Law or grant, but it is onely declaratory of the Law of <hi>England. And this,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſhould admoniſh Parliaments, that in ſtead of this pretious trial by the Law of the Land, they bring not in abſolute, and partial trials by diſcretion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> That it is againſt the Prudence, and Juſtice of the King; and against his lawful Oath.</head>
               <p>AS the ſelling Biſhops Lands is againſt our Lawes, which the two Houſes, and Kingdome, by their ſeverall Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, Proteſtations, and Covenants, have ſolemnly bound themſelves to maintain; ſo it is againſt the Kings <hi>Prudence,</hi> againſt his <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and againſt his lawfull and juſt Oath.</p>
               <p>It is againſt the Kings <hi>Prudence</hi> to deveſt, and rob himſelf of thoſe Immunities,<note place="margin">25 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.20. 26 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.3. <hi>and</hi> 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 4. 14 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5</note> Rights, Profits, and Revenues, which the Law of this Land hath ſettled in the Crown: as, Colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Biſhopricks, Firſt-fruits, and Tenths.</p>
               <p>It is againſt the Kings <hi>Justice,</hi> to take or make that away from his Heires and Succeſſours, which by our Lawes are juſtly and rightly granted unto them; and theſe Rights the two Kingdomes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> have ſworn to maintain.</p>
               <p>It is againſt his <hi>Juſtice,</hi> to doe, or ſuffer it to be done, in reſpect of the Biſhops, to whom the King, as the fountaine of Juſtice, is bound to ſee Juſtice done, (as to his Subjects in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral;)<note place="margin">2. <hi>Inſtitut.</hi> 1.</note> but then, conſidering, from S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Edward Coke,</hi> that by our old Law-books, the Church is ever under age, and in the cuſtody or guardian-ſhip of the King, who is bound to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and defend the Rights and Inheritances of the Church, and that it cannot be agreeable to Right and Juſtice, that Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pils under age, through the negligence, or default of the Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians ſhould ſuffer loſſe, or diſinheritance, I pray, well
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115963:15"/>weigh, whether it wil not amount even to a crying ſinne in the King, to doe, or ſuffer ſuch an injuſtice to be done to his Pupil, the Church, deſtitute of all help on earth, ſave onely what ſhe may juſtly expect from the King? <hi>Solomon</hi> the wiſeſt King on earth, from the Spirit of God hath ſpoken it; <hi>Enter not into the fields of the Fatherleſſe, for their Redeemer is mighty, and he ſhal plead their cauſe with thee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.10, 11</note> And when you wel conſider and weigh, what an Oath the King hath taken at his Coronation, you cannot, I beleeve, acquit the King of a flat perjury, if hee ſhall aſſent to the ſelling away of the Biſhops Lands.</p>
               <p>But what I ſhal urge in this point, is not ſo much to inform the King, (who I am verily perſwaded by the illumination of Gods Spirit, his frequent reading the holy Scriptures, and by the Principles received from his moſt religious and learned Father, of ever bleſſed memory, is ſo fully ſatisfied and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, that neither height nor depth, nor any creature, ſhall be able to ſeparate or deterr him, from the juſt defence of the Church;) as to let the world ſee, that it was not (as ſome igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly, and uncharitably may term it) pertinacity in the King, not to aſſent to the deſtruction of the Church eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, but the dictate of a good conſcience rightly informed. And that it may well be ſo, be pleaſed to hear and conſider what, how, to whom, where, when, the King ſwears. For being to be Crowned King of <hi>England,</hi> in the convention or preſence of his Nobles, Clergy, and People in the Church, the Biſhop askes the King; Sir, will you grant, and keep, and by your Oath confirm the Lawes, Cuſtomes, and Franchiſes granted to the Clergy, according to the Lawes of God? The King anſwers, I grant and promiſe to keep them. Then the Biſhop ſpeakes to the King; Our Lord and King, we beſeech you to grant and preſerve to us, and to the Churches com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to our charge, all Canonical Privileges, and due Lawes, and Juſtice; and that you would protect, and defend us, as every good King ought to be a Protector and Defender of the Biſhops, and Churches under his Government. The King anſwers, with a willing and devout heart, I promiſe, and grant, that I will preſerve, and maintaine to you, and the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115963:16"/>Churches committed to your charge, all Canonical Privileges, and due Law, and Juſtice; and that I wil be your Protector, and Defender, to my power, by the aſſiſtance of God, as every good King in his Kingdome, by right ought to protect and defend the Biſhops, and Churches under his government.</p>
               <p>Then the King at the Communion Table, makes a ſolemn Oath, in the ſight of all the people, laying his hand upon the holy Book, and ſaith: The things that I have before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, I ſhall perform, and keep: So help me God, and the contents of this Booke.</p>
               <p>Now, I beſeech you all good Chriſtians, judge whether this be not an Oath, able, with feare and reverence, to bind the King to the performance? For 1. it is taken by the King, Gods Anointed. 2. In Gods Houſe, the holy Church. 3. At Gods holy Table. 4. Upon Gods holy Book. 5. Tendered by Gods Miniſters, the Biſhops. 6. In the preſence, ſight and hearing of Gods people. 7. To defend Gods ſervants the Biſhops, and the Church. 8. With the imprecation of Gods curſes, and forfeiture of Gods bleſſings, in caſe of not performance: ſo that, if ever Oath could truely be called the Oath of God, this is it.</p>
               <p>And yet, if I miſtake not, there is ſomewhat more that adds ſtrength to the Obligation of this Oath; and that is, That it is upon a contract betwixt the King and the Biſhops; for ſo the Oath is tendered to the King, by, and for the Biſhops: and from ſuch a Contract and Oath, if juſt and lawfull, (as this is) who can abſolve, but he alone, who is concerned, and to, and for whom the Oath and Contract is made, which are onely God, and the Biſhops?</p>
               <p>I have caſt mine eye upon a Treatiſe touching the Kings Oath, publiſhed by Order, and written by Mr <hi>Geree,</hi> Preacher of Gods Word at Saint <hi>Albans:</hi> wherein hee goes about to perſwade, that the King, without impeachment of his Oath at his Coronation, may aſſent to the aboliſhing of Epiſcopacy. I cannot, without a great digreſſion, anſwer his Arguments, which might eaſily be done from his own words and grounds: but in ſtead thereof, I ſhall ſet down his own words, whence I hope it will appeare clearly, that the King cannot, ſaving
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115963:16"/>that his Oath, aſſent to the ſelling away the Church Lands.</p>
               <p>His words are theſe, <hi>The intention of that Oath is not againſt Legal wayes of change, but against invaſion of the Rights of the Clergy.</hi> So that, if ſelling the Lands of the Church be ſuch an invaſion, then he profeſſeth, that the King by his Oath, is bound from it: and whether it be ſo or no in his ſenſe and judgement, heare himſelfe ſpeake in the ſame Treatiſe, where he expreſly ſaith; <hi>To aboliſh Prelacy, and to ſeize the lands of Prelates to any private, or civil intereſt, undoubtedly, could neither want staine, nor guilt.</hi> So that by the plaine expreſſe verdict of this Preacher of Gods Word, the King is proclaimed before hand, to be a man of a ſtained and guilty conſcience, if he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the ſelling Church-Lands, according to the Ordinance: And I am confident, by the diſcourſe I have had with the moſt able of the Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> that at the leaſt three parts, if not all of them, are of the ſame judgement with this Preacher; and that they would openly profeſſe as much, if they were put to anſwer the queſtion.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But ſome perchance will ſay, that the King ſweares all this but to his power; and therefore, his power to defend Biſhops being taken away, he is abſolved from perjury.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                  </label> Too too many, I feare, there are, who by falſe lights have and will miſlead the beſt of Princes and men; and that this is a light of that kind, you wil eaſily diſcerne, when you conſider, that the defence of the Biſhops in this caſe, is onely that the King give not his aſſent to the ſelling of Biſhops Lands: And who can ſay, but that this is in the Kings power? For who can force him to ſpeake? or to ſpeake what another will? or that which is againſt his own will to ſpeake? And therefore, if he doe aſſent to the ſelling their lands, he defends them not to his power, and thereby falls into an irreparable perjury, and becomes liable to the puniſhments, due and threatned in Gods Law: one place for many,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 5.4.</note> Perjury <hi>ſhal remain in the midſt of the houſe of him that ſweareth falſly, and ſhal conſume it;</hi> by which houſe is not onely meant the material houſe of timber and ſtone, but (as often in Scripture) his wife, children, and poſterity; it ſhall conſume them. Yea, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Geree,</hi> above men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115963:17"/>confeſſeth, <hi>That the King by his Oath is bound to protect the Church, ſo far as he can, without ſinning and being injurious:</hi> now in not aſſenting, againſt whom ſins he, being not bound by any Law to aſſent? Whereas, if he doe aſſent, he is pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pably injurious to the Church; and therefore this Author concludes thus, <hi>Then the King, at the worſt, is to get the Clergies aſſent:</hi> Wherein he ſeemes to implie, that without that, the King juſtly may not give his aſſent; and he gives his reaſon for it in the ſame place; where he ſaith, <hi>The King may not engage himſelfe againſt the Lawes, and legal Rights of others: For that were</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>not cedere jure ſuo</hi> but <hi>alieno, to give away another mans right, which is unjuſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wil you give me leave to put you a Scripture caſe? The Gibeonites, (by Nation, Heathen; by Religion, Idolatrous,) by fraud and a lie, gain from <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and the Princes of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, a promiſe to protect them;<note place="margin">Joſh. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> Now obſerve, although this promiſe was fraudulently obtained, and raſhly made, without asking Gods counſel, or the conſent of the people; yea, although it was againſt that which was enjoyned Iſrael, (which was to deſtroy all the Nations,) how zealous God is, that an Oath be kept, which is made in his Name, for his honour, and whereof he is a witneſſe; That, becauſe <hi>Saul</hi> brake this League or Covenant with the Gibeonites, above three hundred yeares after, when a man would hardly have conceived that King <hi>Saul</hi> had been bound to perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of it;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.</note> I ſay, for the breach of that fraudulently got, and raſhly made Covenant, God puiſheth the whole <hi>land with a famine for three yeares, yeare after yeare;</hi> and yet would not be pacified, without the hanging up of almoſt all <hi>Sauls</hi> poſterity. And if God be ſo ſevere a Judge, in ſuch a caſe as this; what can the King, or this Land expect from heaven, if he ſhould, after much conſultation, long deliberation, and the many proteſtations, (as I am informed) that it is againſt his conſcience, violate ſo juſt, ſo holy an Oath as this?</p>
               <p>But, I truſt, the King, though he had never taken ſuch an Oath, will in his frequent reading Gods holy Word, conſider that act (before mentioned) of King <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> who,<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>47.</hi>
                  </note> in that greateſt caſe of extremity, famine, would
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115963:17"/>not then ſuffer the <hi>Prieſts lands</hi> to be ſold; and the rather I hope the King will remember and conſider that act of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 2.26.</note> becauſe the <hi>Biſhops</hi> (as K. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpake of <hi>Abiathar</hi> the high Prieſt) <hi>have bean afflicted in all as the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faith,</hi> ſaith our old Proteſtant Religion, <hi>s to be kept with Idolaters and Hereticks,</hi> whom we hold the worſt of men; and muſt a pious Proteſtant King be forced to breake it with the beſt of his Subjects? O how will the enemies of our Religion blaſpheme for this! and what King, or Nation, will hereafter truſt our King, who in breaking ſo juſt, and ſolemne an Oath, as that at his Coronation, wil rob his God, loſe his faith, forfeit his ſoule, deſtroy agoodly flouriſhing Church, and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly undo them, who have hazarded all, thereby to keep loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, and a good conſcience? I cloſe this point with this wiſh, that all they who preſſe the King, contrary to his Oath, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the alienation of Biſhops Lands, would remember that Juſtice <hi>Triſilian</hi> was hanged for cauſing,<note place="margin">Speed Chron. in Rich. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> or procuring the King to breake his Oath; as it hath beene often urged in this Parliament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> One and twenty Arguments, which are brought in defence of or colour for ſuch Alienation, are anſwered.</head>
               <p>BUt avarice, pride, ill affections, or finiſter ends, I feare (notwithſtanding what hath, or may further be alleged) will urge, what I ſhall here endevour to anſwer.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>1</label> God is not the proprietarie of Biſhops Lands, more then he is of the whole Creation; and therefore, we may as well ſell thoſe, as any other lands in the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Tis true, <hi>The earth is the Lords, and the fulneſſe thereof;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reſp. Pſa.</hi> 24.11.</note> all are Gods by Creation, Providence, and Preſervation; yet when God hath given them to man, they are the mans, and he in our Law language is become the Proprietarie; which is no more then Sr <hi>Edward Coke</hi> ſaith, What is given to Church-men, is given to God, and it is then Gods. Yea, in Gods word,<note place="margin">Instit. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> Saint
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115963:18"/>
                  <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith of <hi>Ananias</hi> his land, <hi>While it was thine owne, was it not in thine owne power?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 5.4.</note> But when men ſhal give this againe to God and that God accepts it, then it is as plainly Gods again, and God is the Proprietarie of it, as of his own. Proved like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe from the ſame Text, where after <hi>Ananias</hi> his dedication, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, that he did <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, with a lie deceive God,<note place="margin">Ver. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> in that he did <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, purloyne or cheat God of that which was now become Gods. Yea, and Chriſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting as his, what was given to his Diſciples and Apoſtles, makes himſelfe, by the acceptation thereof, a Proprietarie of that too;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.40.</note> ſo he profeſſeth, <hi>In that ye have given meate and drinke to theſe my Brethren, ye have given it to me;</hi> and what is given to me, is mine, as well as what I might have purchaſed, or might come to me by deſcent;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.1.</note> and that by theſe <hi>Brothren,</hi> may rightly be underſtood his Diſciples and Apoſtles, read <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. 1. where he cals his twelve Diſciples, whom he ſends to preach; and then in the cloſe, ſpeaking of them, he ſaith, <hi>Who receiveth you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. <hi>40.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>receiveth me.</hi> And accordingly, Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> as I before proved, maketh Sacrilege, or taking away holy things, a breach of the firſt Table, which concerneth God: which could not be, unleſſe God were the Proprietarie, and owner of them; but of ſuch diſputers, I may ſay as Chriſt did of thoſe Jewes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark</hi> 12.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Do you not erre, becauſe you know not the Scriptures, nor the power of God?</hi> What need we plainer proofe then our owne Law, when as the great Charter ſpeaking now in the name of King and people in Parliament ſaith, We have gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to God, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>2</label> But the great Charter, on which the Biſhops ſo much relie, was probably penned, or gained by Biſhops, and it was granted in time of Poperie, and ſavours too much of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> If the great Charter were obtained or penned by Biſhops, I know not but all Engliſhmen ſhould rather commend, then blame them for it; for it is the beſt flower in <hi>Englands</hi> garden: and I preſume, it ſavours not of Poperie, but to ſuch as have their ſenſes ſtopped, or themſelves ill affected. But if there be any Poperie proved in the Grant, take that away in Gods name, but let the Rights and the Lands continue; for I know not how theſe can be capable of Poperie: But wil all others
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115963:18"/>who receive benefit by that Charter, hold it null, becauſe gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in time of Poperie? I trow not. That which ſilences all ſuch cavils, is that, as before it is proved, this Charter was, and is but the declaration, and confirmation of the ancient Law of this Kingdome, and therefore ought to hold and bind. and then let me adde, the firſt Impropriations in <hi>England</hi> were in time of Poperie, and by Popes, who of 9284. Pariſhes, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated the Tithes of 3845. of the beſt of them; which Tithes now for the moſt part, are in Lay hands. And thou that abhorreſt Poperie, committeſt thou Sacrilege? For we ſay, the Receiver is worſe then the Thiefe: Or why rather ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horreſt not thou that act? And why reſtoreſt not thou the Tithes being Sacrilegiouſly taken?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>3</label> But theſe, or many of theſe Lands of the Biſhops, were given as by ſuperſtitious men, and in ſuperſtitious times, ſo to ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious uſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> Who doubts not but many good, lawful, and religious acts, may have been performed in ſuperſtitious times, and by ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious perſons? Time or perſon do not, I am ſure ſhould not, denominate the act ſimply good or ill. But was King <hi>Lucius,</hi> who <hi>An.</hi> 176. gave the Church in <hi>England</hi> Lands, was he ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious? Or thoſe times ſuch? Who can prove it? But which are the ſuperſtitious uſes in Biſhops lands? Are they Preaching, keeping Hoſpitality, doing acts of Piety, Juſtice, Charity, paying the King his due, and ſerving the Publike? For I finde no worſe. But grant there were ſome ſuperſtitious uſes in the firſt Grant, yet why ſhall the lands be taken and ſold, if the abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be by the Biſhops, or other wayes taken away? And M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Geree</hi> before mentioned, <hi>pag.</hi> 19. ſaith it, What was Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and contrariant to the Lawes of this Land, was taken from the Church in the reigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth. And though the impulſive cauſe of giving ſome lands might be ill, (as to pray for the ſoules of the dead, or the like) yet the final cauſe being good, as given to God, why not ſeparate the ill, (take away praying for the dead and the like) all which is done, and yet continue the good, the keeping the Lands for Gods Honour and Service? For read you not that the bullock which was ſet apart for the Sacrifice of <hi>Baal,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Judg.</hi> 6.26.</note> yet <hi>Gideon</hi> ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115963:19"/>it to the Lord, becauſe it was not then in ſtate Idolatrous? Things, I confeſſe, which have and retaine the matter, forme, and dependence on Idols, (as having the badge of Idolatry) theſe are not to be offered or continued to God and his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; which Biſhops Lands neither had, nor have, no not ſo much as is continued in the City of <hi>Londons</hi> Armes, or ſome great mens Coates; they have not ſo much as a Croſſe on them. But if all ſhould be taken away, that hath been given to ſuperſtitious uſes, what would become of our Churches? and if all aboliſhed that hath been abuſed, what would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of our Pulpits, Communion Tables, Sacraments? yea, of Parliaments, or that moſt adored peece of Gods Service, Preaching?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.2.</note> In a word, the cenſers are by wicked perſons, to as wicked ends, abuſed by <hi>Korah,</hi> and his complices; what then? are they therefore ſold, or turned into pots, kettles, or the like? (the like whereof hath been done in our times) no, but they were by Gods owne ordinance, preſerved in their holy kind:<note place="margin">Ver. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> and that becauſe, as it is expreſſed in the Text, <hi>They were hallowed to the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>4</label> But the King, it is ſaid, is bound to confirme what the two Houſes have decreed; and they have ordained the ſelling of the Biſhops Lands.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> I ſhall paſſe by that ſo often fully anſwered, <hi>(Elegerint,)</hi> and ſhall confidently ſay, that the King is no more bound to aſſent to what they decree, then they are bound to decree, and to ſell the Biſhops Lands, to which they are not bound, if the thing be not juſt and agreeable to the Law of God and man: which whether ſo or no,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 4, 5, 6.</note> I deſire you conſider what is before expreſſed. The Precept of God, I hope, in your judgements holds,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not follow a multitude to doe evil:</hi> againe, if that, which appeares good and juſt to the two Houſes, be evil in the conſcience of the King, the King is not bound, nay he ought not to joyne with the two Houſes: for Proteſtants, as they rightly hold no ſalvation by implicite faith; ſo neither that one mans conſcience ſhould ride upon the backe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: ſo that, although ſome in Parliament may in part be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed in doing that which is not juſt, through the falſe gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of an erring conſcience; yet the King in doing the ſame
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115963:19"/>thing, againſt the light of his conſcience, may ſinne; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon further it may become a fearfull ſinne by any tentation of promiſes, threats, reſtraints, to draw or drive the King to aſſent to what his conſcience forbids him to doe.</p>
               <p>Againe, the caſe betwixt the King and the two Houſes, in ſelling the Biſhops Lands, is very different; for the King is bound by Oath to the Biſhops to maintaine them, and their Rights, in their lands and poſſeſſions, according to Law and Juſtice: to which the two Houſes ſtand not alike, and ſo deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obliged; whereupon it followes, I conceive, that though the two Houſes might, (the contrary whereof is before proved) yet the King ought not to give his aſſent.</p>
               <p>Laſtly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Jac. <hi>3.</hi> Coke Inſtit. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> the King (as the Act of Parliament ſtiles him) is the <hi>Patron of the Biſhops Lands;</hi> and our Common Law makes him the Churches Guardian; and is the King bound to follow others, who have not the like charge or duty on them? and ſo defraud a Pupil, whom by Gods and mans Law, his own Oath, and conſcience, he is bound to defend and maintaine? The Biſhop doing fealty, the King holds the Biſhops hands betwixt his owne; which, ſaith S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Edward Coke</hi> from <hi>Bracton, Britton,</hi> and others, ſhewes, that the King promiſeth him <hi>protectionem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Inſtit. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>1.</hi> Sect. <hi>85.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>defenſionem, &amp; warrantiam:</hi> And addes, that <hi>this the King pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth to him, not as to a Subject, but as to a Biſhop; and not to his perſon alone, but to his poſſeſſions.</hi> And this S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Edward Coke</hi> cals <hi>Foedus</hi> from <hi>Fides,</hi> and termes it <hi>Sacramentum Fidelitatis:</hi> which therefore the King may not, upon other mens judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and conſciences, breake. Conſider, I pray, what the wiſeſt King on earth counſelled all Kings, and others; <hi>Be not raſh with thy mouth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.2, 4.</note> 
                  <hi>and let not thy heart be haſty to utter any thing or word before God: but when thou vowost a vow to God, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre not to pay it, for he hath no pleaſure in fooles, pay that which thou haſt vowed.</hi> And which comes home to the vow and thing vowed, <hi>It is a ſnare to devoure holy things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.20.</note> 
                  <hi>and after the vow to make enquiry, i.e.</hi> how to breake it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>5</label> But the King hath aſſented to as much in <hi>Scotland,</hi> thereby to gratifie his people there; and why not then to doe as much for his Parliament in <hi>England?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> It cannot be denied, but that the beſt of Kings, as of other
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115963:20"/>men, have had their lapſes; but they are ſo far from being bound, after the ſight and ſenſe of an error, to fall into the ſame againe; that on the contrary, they are obliged to repent, and eſchew the like for ever. 2. What the King, in that caſe, there hath done, whether it were voluntary or compulſory, ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or deliberately, I cannot tell; onely this I ſay, if through paſſion, ill counſel, or the like, he did that once there, which ſhould not have been done: it followes not that hee may or ſhould doe the like againe, or here. But 3. we are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand whether the Biſhops ſtood ſo enſtated in their lands in that Kingdome, as the Biſhops doe in <hi>England.</hi> 4. But eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to know, whether the King ſtood bound to God, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> by the ſame, or ſuch Contracts, Oathes, Charters, as he ſtands in <hi>England;</hi> wherein if there be a difference, as I verily perſwade my ſelf there is, then it will not follow, the King did it in <hi>Scotland,</hi> therefore he may or ſhould doe it in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>6</label> Yet Parliaments have alienated Biſhops Lands, whereby they may plead it as a Privilege to doe the like.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> I cannot ſay that one Act, (ſcarce an hundred years old) can make or warrant a Privilege; for no juſt Privilege can be indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, but upon acts rightly and lawfully grounded: And M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> from Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">De neceſ. refor. Eccleſ. Chap. <hi>4, 5, 6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Privilegium meretur amittere, qui Privilegio abutitur.</hi> So that if it be true (which I laid down before,) that it is a ſin to alienate ſuch Lands, then <hi>à factoad jus non ſequitur Argumentum:</hi> it hath been unjuſtly done, therefore it may be lawfully done, a Plough-man will ſay holds not. Now to affix, or conceive an inerrability in a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, is, I hope, more then the Parliament will aſſume to themſelves; we Proteſtants have denied it to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ball. Catoples.</note> nay, their <hi>own greatest Jeſuits</hi> diſclaime it in matter of fact. But if a hundred years ſithence, the King in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament uſed this power to alienate Church Lands, yet not much above forty years agoe,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Jac.</hi> 3.</note> in King <hi>James</hi> his time, the Parliament, without the King, waved the having any ſuch power or privilege; For that Act ſhewes, that the two Houſes in Parliament, had not power to hinder Biſhops from making Leaſes to the Crown, for above one and twenty yeares, or
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115963:20"/>three lives; and how in this ſhort time, the Power and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege is ſo vaſtly encreaſed, I know not, except it be by the Sword, which kind of Power, as it was never held the beſt, ſo it hath not ever proved long liv'd, or, I am ſure, not ever peacefull. <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> might have argued thus, I uſe but thoſe holy veſſels, which my father in a lawful war, hath gained from a common enemy, and left them ſo to me his Heir and Succeſſour. And did not the rebellious Iſraelites ſeem to plead the like?<note place="margin">Mal. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> We doe but deteine the Offerings as our Fathers have done before us. And doth God admit of theſe? No, their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription he uſeth as an aggravation of their offence, ſaying, <hi>From the dayes of your Fathers ye have departed from mine Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ver.</hi> 7. <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.11.</note> and therefore, heare Gods ſentence on both <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> and Iſrael; where the King is puniſhed with loſſe of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and a ſudden fearful death; and Iſrael is ſtrooke with a lamentable deſtroying famine; and ſuch are Gods juſt rewards upon unjuſt Privileges, and unlawful Preſcriptions.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>7</label> But a Parliament may take away any mans lands in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; for this is an inherent, and inſeparable power of Parliaments.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> The Rule is good, <hi>Id poſſumus, quod jure &amp; justè poſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus:</hi> We are not truly ſaid, to may, or can do any thing, but that which we can, or may juſtly doe: Now, if it be, (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I proved) againſt Gods, and mans Law, and Juſtice, to ſell away Biſhops Lands, then the Parliament may not doe it. For the Parliament, this Parliament often hath declared, and ſworn to maintain the Lawes of this Kingdom, which are utterly againſt ſuch Alienation. The Jewes are told,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.</note> the King ſhall take their ſons, their fields, &amp;c. and they ſhall find no help: What, I pray, is the ſenſe and extent of that power in the King? Is it, that by his juſt Right he might doe all that is ſpoken of him in that Chapter; becauſe it is ſaid,<note place="margin">Ver. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> this will be the manner and cuſtome of the King ſo to doe? Ask the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and I doubt not but they will tell you, that if that, King, and Sanedrin, and all Iſrael, joyntly go beyond the Word of God, and the Laws preſcribed to them, all their power could not ſave them from the guilt of ſin, nor reprieve them from Gods ſevere wrath.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:115963:21"/>
               <p>When the lands were given, as moſt were, in the Saxon Kings times, I dare ſay, it cannot be proved, that there was ſuch power in the Nobility and people, as to ſell away the Church-Lands: for the firſt large Grant or power of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, was in <hi>Henry</hi> the Third's time; and the ſame King it was, that granted the Charter, wherein is expreſt, that the Rights of the Church ſhall be ever inviolable: Now if that Charter, and thoſe Parliaments ſay, the Rights of the Church in ſpecial, cannot, may not, by any power, be violated or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away; doe they yet grant ſuch a power to Parliaments to take thoſe Rights away, and ſo expreſly contradict them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? And can you conceive that King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, who firſt granted that Charter, and gave the right Power to Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, would have ſuffered the two Houſes, yea, or that himſelfe, would after that Grant, made to the Church, have decreed, that he might juſtly uſe the power of Parliament to ſell thoſe Lands? Or can you conceive, that thoſe Kings who gave the Biſhops Lands, (for ſo it is ſaid, that the Kings of <hi>England</hi> gave them,) and that with ſuch curſes on their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours, or any who ſhould dare to alienate, or ſell them, ever meant they ſhould be ſold? And tell me, I pray, for I am to learne, where ever good and lawful Parliament, did ever take away any ſingle mans whole eſtate, though it were to pay the Publike debt, or for Publike uſe, except it were in a legal courſe? And can you conceive, that the two Houſes may doe that to the inheritance of God, the Patronage of the King, and the Rights of the Church, which they cannot do to him, who hath yeelded up his aſſent, by giving his Vote to his Proxie in Parliament; which neither God, the King, nor the Church hath done,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>700.</hi>
                  </note> in this Parliament? I pray you conſider, that in the Book of your Declarations, it is ſaid, That the Rights of Publike truſt, are not to the prejudice of any mans particular intereſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>8</label> And if it be yet urged, that Parliaments may change the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicipal Lawes of this Kingdom; and therefore, much more, this of the Title, or Tenure of Biſhops Lands.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> I think, I may rightly anſwer, that the King, and all the people of <hi>England,</hi> by a mutual aſſent, may change the general
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115963:21"/>Laws, or ſuch Laws, as they hold ſitting and convenient to be altered, for their better good; for here is neither injury, nor injuſtice to any; but yet ſpecial Laws, which concerne the good of ſome in ſpeciall, (I conceive with humble ſubmiſſion) may not juſtly be changed, except it be by the aſſent, perſonal Vote, or Proxie, of thoſe intereſſed: none of which can here be ſaid of the Church, or Biſhops; or unleſſe ſome offence lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſuch a penalty hath demerited ſuch a ſentence or change of that ſpecial Law; and that no ſuch offence hath been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted deſerving ſuch a penalty, I preſume to be true, for that the Biſhops have not been legally accuſed, heard and tried, which was ever the ordinary and right courſe uſed by the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes, Romans, and all Religious, good, and Civil Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and which is the Law of this Kingdome,<note place="margin">Ch. <hi>14.</hi> &amp; <hi>29.</hi>
                  </note> as is expreſſed in the great Charter. But, I feare, theſe two laſt Arguments, and many more ſuch, are built on ſands, which waſhed, or driven away with a little wind, all the building fals to the ground: for they take it for granted, that the two Houſes, or rather that ſome Lords Temporal and Commons make the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for the diſcovery whereof, I pray conſider, 1. The conception: 2. The birth: 3. The growth and ſtrength of Parliaments.</p>
               <p>In the Saxon times, when the ſeed or conception of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments was, at the making, conſirming, or witneſſing Laws, ſeldome is there any mention, but of the King, and the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, (except the Kings Servants, Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,<note place="margin">Spelm. Concil.</note> ſome wiſe men, &amp;c.) Nay, when our Parliaments firſt were borne, in the nineth and twentieth of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, there is no mention then, but of the King, and the Lords Spiritual and Temporal. Yea, at the Grant of the great Charter, there is only mention of one and thirty Lords Spiritual, and two and thirty Lords Temporal,<note place="margin">Coke Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. to <hi>2</hi> Inſtit. Mat. Par. p. <hi>435</hi> Id. pag. <hi>580.</hi> &amp; <hi>581.</hi> Id. p. <hi>636.</hi>
                  </note> in the one and twentieth of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, in Parliament at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster.</hi> And in the one and thirtieth of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third at <hi>London,</hi> which were for the relief of the diſtreſſed Kingdome, yet there were only mentioned, the King, and the whole Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Kingdome: <hi>viz.</hi> the Biſhops, Prelates, Earles and Barons. But in the two and fiftieth of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, ſay
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115963:22"/>our printed Statutes, <hi>The King providing for the Estate of this Realm, the more diſcreet men of the Kingdome being called, as well of the higher, as the lower eſtate, the King hath made theſe Acts, Ordinances, and Statutes, which he willeth to be obſerved of all for ever:</hi> And ſo the formes of Acts in Parliament ran, The King willeth, provideth, ordaineth, granteth. In the 31 <hi>Henry</hi> 6.1. <hi>The King ordaines, by the advice and aſſent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſaid Parliament.</hi> In 1 <hi>Rich.</hi> 3.6. <hi>The Commons pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that it may pleaſe the King to ordaine.</hi> 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 3. We the <hi>Lords Spiritual, and Temporal, and Commons, repreſenting the three Eſtates of the Realme of England, make our humble peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to your Highneſſe:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ch. of Parl. fol. <hi>1</hi>
                  </note> Whereupon, ſaith S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Edward Coke, With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out theſe three, Lords Spiritual, and Temporal, and Commons, no Act of Parliament can be good;</hi> and rightly, for as all the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in <hi>England</hi> have Votes, ſo the Biſhops vote for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and all the Church-men in <hi>England.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, if they have no Votes in Parliament, then either they are the onely ſlaves, and no Free-men; or elſe thoſe Church-men are not bound by theſe Lawes: it being a Maxime in our Law, that no man is bound to that Law, wherein he had no Vote in perſon, or by Proxie; which no Biſhop, and I think no Church-man, hath now in this Parliament.</p>
               <p>But, not to diſpute this, though agreeable to all Law, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and Reaſon; yet ſure it cannot be rightly called a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, or any Act therein binding, without the Kings Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al aſſent: for as in a natural body, ſo in this, no life, nor mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without a Head, which is the King; yea, therefore he is called <hi>Principium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>4</hi> Part Instit. ſ. <hi>3, 4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Caput, Finis Parliamenti:</hi> becauſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the King, or his Royal aſſent, it is no binding Act. See but one Act for many, 1 <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. where it is thus ſaid, <hi>We the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, beſeech your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>which if your Majeſty ſhall be pleaſed to adorne with your Majeſties Royal aſſent, without which it can neither be complete and perfect,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In anſwer to Judge Jenkin.</note> 
                  <hi>nor remaine to poſterity.</hi> And 1. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</hi> 7. the two Houſes beſeech the King, to give his Royal aſſent to ſuch Bils as they then paſſed; and <hi>H. P.</hi> confeſſes, (which was never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied till of late, and that but by ſome) that no Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115963:22"/>can be complete, or formally binding, without the Kings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ent. And ſo M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Prynne</hi> affirmes,<note place="margin">Power of Parl. f. <hi>47.</hi> Ib. fol. <hi>104.</hi> In his Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. p. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> that the Kings aſſent is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally requiſite to paſſe Lawes, and ratifie them. And Judge <hi>Jenkins,</hi> that undanted Champion of our Lawes, affirmes, that in all ages, without any controverſie, this hath held ſo, that no Act of Parliament bindes the Subject of this Land, without the aſſent of the King, either for perſon, lands, goods, or ſame; and refers you to Sr <hi>Edward Coke,</hi> where many Law-books are cited to that purpoſe.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> part Inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it. ſect. <hi>234.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>The ignorant or wilful miſtake of divers, holding the two Houſes, and their Ordinances, to be truly called Parliaments, and Acts of Parliaments; as it hath deceived many in their conſciences, and of their lives, ſo may it in this of their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys, if not timely foreſeen, and prevented.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>9</label> But, though the King, in his natural capacity and power, be perſonally abſent from the two Houſes, yet his Politick power and capacity, is virtually in them; and therefore, what the two Houſes ordain, muſt as neceſſarily bind, as if the King were perſonally preſent with them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> In anſwer to this, I pray conſider, what that great Lawyer Mr <hi>Plowden,</hi> and Sr <hi>Edward Coke,</hi> have determined for Law;<note place="margin">Comment. f. <hi>21<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> &amp; <hi>242.</hi> In Calv. Caſe.</note> and they ſay, that the Natural, and the Politick body of the King, make but one body; for as long as the Natural body lives, the Politick is inherent in it, this being a thing imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, and inviſible. And, I pray, conſider how well our Law may be called Holy, in that it agrees ſo well with Gods own holy Law;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2.</note> for ſo Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of the Politick power not to be reſiſted, ſettles this power in the perſon of the King, to whom it belongeth, when he ſaith,<note place="margin">Ver. <hi>3.</hi> Ver. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Wilt thou not feare the power? then doe that which is good, for He,</hi> not they, <hi>is the Ruler, and He,</hi> not they, <hi>it the Miniſter of God.</hi> And Saint <hi>Peter</hi> differs not, but rather declares the ſame, when he thus ſpeakes;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Submit your ſelves to the King as ſupreme;</hi> and, <hi>honour the King:</hi> and what can hence be leſſe inferred then this, that the power, whereby he is a King, and his Supremacy, whereby he is above all, naturally reſteth in the perſon of the King? and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>he</hi> is to be honoured for his power, and <hi>he</hi> to be ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto, becauſe <hi>he is King and Supreme.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:115963:23"/>
               <p>Now, can any man reaſonably conceive, that this power being an eſſential accident inhering in the King, ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> without the Kings conſent and will, vaniſh from its own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſubject, and be of it ſelfe truly inherent in another ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, which is not capable of ſuch an accident? I ſay not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, for the two Houſes being and remaining Subjects, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe their owne uſual ſtile, <hi>We Your Majeſties humble Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> are not a ſubject capable of Supremacie, in that Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie and Subjection are oppoſite Relatives; and therefore cannot be, at one and the ſame time, in one and the ſame ſubject.</p>
               <p>The King, I grant, though bodily abſent, yet may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent repreſentatively, in the two Houſes, ſpeaking either by his great Seal, or by his Commiſſioners, by himſelf appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which hath been often uſed in our Parliaments: but to ſay, that his power is in the two Houſes, without his will, or grant, is all one, as if we ſhould ſay, the influence of the Sun ſhould be inherent in the earth, without the natural inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or motion of the Sun: ſeeing that as no body can be the proper ſubject wherein that influence doth naturally inhere, but the Sun; ſo no body, nor perſons, can be the proper ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to containe, and hold Royal Power and Supremacie, but the perſon of the King, or they to whom he will, as the Sun, diſpenſe the rayes or influence thereof.</p>
               <p>And if it hath been, or now may otherwiſe be, why, I pray, both now, as heretofore, have, and doe the two Houſes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate, deſire, crave, and beſeech the King, to give his Royal aſſent, which naturally ariſeth from that his Politick capacity and power, thereby to make that Law, without which Royal aſſent, no man worthy the name of a Lawyer, ever held that any Bill, Decree, or Ordinance, was of force to bind the Subject, as to a ſtanding and continuing Law? which is plainly ſhewed in Anſwer to the Argument next before. But, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that an Act made by the King, Lords, and Commons, doth bind; yet if that Act be (as I before have proved this Ordinance of ſelling the Church-Lands to be) againſt Gods and mans Laws, it is to be repealed, becauſe it is unlawful and unjuſt, ſo to ordain or enact; and the Parliament ſhould do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt Law and Juſtice.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:115963:23"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>10</label> I have read this Argument in print, that God no where commands ſuch Lands to be given, or Biſhops to hold them; and therefore, where no breach of a Commandement is, there is no ſin.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> It appears, that King <hi>David</hi> intended to build an houſe to the Lord, but the Lord would not that <hi>David</hi> ſhould build it; and yet the Lord ſaid, <hi>David did well,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Reg</hi> 8.17, 18, 19.</note> 
                  <hi>that it was in his heart to doe it:</hi> God commended, and accepted of <hi>Davids</hi> act, although that act were no where commanded to King <hi>David.</hi> And in <hi>Ezra,</hi> mention is made of the free-will-offerings of thoſe, <hi>who offered willingly for the Houſe of the Lord:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezra</hi> 1.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.</note> whereas elſewhere, under the Law, the general precept for Free-will-offerings to God, his Houſe, and Servants, is avowed to be a part of Gods Service, although the particular offerings, of what, how much, is left, un-commanded, to every mans liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to give this or that, more or leſſe, as God ſhall put into his heart. And although there be no particular command to this or that man, to give this or that to Gods Service, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, yet under the general Precepts,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Luke</hi> 6.38.</note> 
                  <hi>Honour the Lord with thy ſubstance;</hi> and, <hi>Give, and it ſhall be given unto you;</hi> there is war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant enough, if not Precept, according to every mans ability, freely to give, and offer to God for his Honour and Service, whether by money, lands, or other goods. Let me a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Where doth Chriſt command the Jewes and Gentiles, to feed and clothe his Diſciples and Apoſtles? What then? Were they not to do it? And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> cals the <hi>Corinthians</hi> Offerings <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.3. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.1.</note> liberality; and the Corban of the Jewes, as before cited, was called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, gifts; now gifts and liberalities are free-offerings, and not duties of command. And ſaith not Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 17.9, 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Doth he thanke that ſervant that did the things commanded? I trow not.</hi> He who will allow God no more then what commanded, ſhall in this robb God of his offerings, the Donors of their reward, and his ſervants of their relief: and it would prove a peſtilent Jewiſh opinion, and too great an enemy to Chriſtianity; which conſiſts, as in voluntary ſufferings, ſo in voluntary offerings, above that which is in ſpecial commanded. To conclude, the Miniſters under the Goſpel hold not their lands by any ſpecial command or Precept from God, but by free-gift of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115963:24"/>man, and by the divine acceptation of God in Chriſt, which is ſufficient in this caſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>11</label> But why then had not the Apoſtles, or their immediate ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, ſuch lands, as well as theſe Biſhops?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> The anſwer is plaine and eaſie; the reaſon why the Apoſtles had not ſuch lands, was not becauſe the Apoſtles, or that God would not have accepted them: for ſure, that God, that accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the feeding and cloathing them, would not have denied them a perpetual certain maintenance: nor was it, becauſe the Chriſtians to their abilities,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 4. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.15.</note> would not have given them lands, as it may appeare by that ſtory in the <hi>Acts,</hi> and by that of Saint <hi>Paul, I bear you record, that you would have plucked out your eyes to have given them to me.</hi> But one reaſon Saint <hi>Chryſoſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> gives, that in the firſt planting of the Goſpel, the Jewes or Gentiles might perchance have ſuppoſed, that the Apoſtles had preached rather for the gaine of their wealth, then for the ſalvation of their ſoules: and who knowes, but that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to that end ſpake that ſentence,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.14.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſeeke not yours but you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, becauſe the Fathers of the Primitive Church are not heard in theſe times, I deſire you to heare Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who for himſelfe, and the other Apoſtles, gives a more full anſwer hereunto,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.11. <hi>Ver.</hi> 12.</note> when he thus ſpeaks; <hi>If we have ſewen unto you ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>gs, is it a great thing, if we ſhall reap your carnal things?</hi> And then, <hi>If others be partakers of this power over you, are not we rather? Nevertheleſſe, we have not uſed this power, but ſuffer all things, leſt we ſhould hinder the Goſpel of Chriſt.</hi> In which words, the Apoſtle evidently ſheweth, that the reap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or maintenance, out of their carnal things, ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that which was ſowed, <hi>viz.</hi> ſpiritual things: and what proportion of carnal things can compenſate for things ſpiritual, let the ſpiritual, and not the carnal man judge. Now the full Anſwer to this Objection, (which S. <hi>Chryſeſtome</hi> might happily collect out of this Text) is this; though we the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles have power to require all this as due, (not of Almes, but morally, as the ſeventh Verſe of that Chapter ſhewes it) yet we uſe it not, leſt we ſhould hinder the Goſpel of Chriſt thereby.</p>
               <p>And yet a ſecond reaſon, that the Apoſtles had not lands for their maintenance, lay in the time, wherein the Apoſtles
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115963:24"/>lived; who, at that time, had not onely no continuing city, or certaine place of abode, <hi>but wandred about,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.37.</note> 
                  <hi>being afflicted and tormented.</hi> Againe, the Romans, the chief lords of all, were ſo far from letting them enjoy any lands at that time, that they hardly afforded them the aire, wherein to breath and live: diſtinguiſh therefore of times, for it holds both in Church and State, <hi>aliter in conſtitutâ vivitur, aliter in conſtituendâ.</hi> At firſt planting of either Church or State, there is neither the ſame Privilege, nor the ſame wealth, but each grow by Gods bleſſing in time.</p>
               <p>And what is here ſpoken of the maintenance, may in part hold for the Government of the Church; that is, that when Saint <hi>Paul</hi> wrote (from whom the moſt is gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, both for the <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> and <hi>Independent</hi>) the Church was not then divided into Pariſhes and Provinces, no, nor into publikely known Congregations: and therefore, it being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der bloudy Perſecution, it could not have the face of a viſible Church: Whereupon, though then the Apoſtle, and Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical men, ordained by him, exerciſed Epiſcopal authority, yet it could not, nor indeed ought it to have been in that height of viſible power; as no doubt Saint <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf would, and thoſe Apoſtolical men did uſe it, ſo ſoon as God had added greater numbers to the Church, and given them favour with the Civil Magiſtrate: the Apoſtle, both for that, and all ſucceeding times, leaving this one general Rule,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40.</note> 
                  <hi>Let all things be done decently, and in order.</hi> And, can any indifferent man hold it juſt and reaſonable, that, when all other men grow in ſtate and wealth, the Church-men alone ſhould decreaſe, and be abuſed? What if I ſhould urge to any Gentleman or others: Your Predeceſſors, two or three hundred years ſince, had not ſuch eſtates, therefore, neither ſhould you, but be content with that which your Forefathers enjoyed? would you hold this Argument to be of force? I doe not in your caſes and, I pray, be you as juſt to us. But, that I be not too tedious, and irk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome in this arguing, let me make an indifferent motion, (which may well ſerve for this Objection) be you now Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, as they were in the times of the Apoſtles, and the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops will be very well content with ſuch maintenance, as the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115963:25"/>Apoſtles had in the times of thoſe Chriſtians; for then the Chriſtians ſold their lands, and goods, and laid the price thereof at the Apoſtles feet: which if you hold unfit now to be done, as I doe; then, I pray, conceive it as unreaſonable to reduce them now to the indigency of the Apoſtles, when all the land beſides, God be praiſed, enjoyes plenty; which the two Houſes have found, both in City and Countrey.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>12</label> But other Reformed Churches have not ſuch Lands, and why this in <hi>England,</hi> rather then they?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> Neither have they perchance Bels, or Chancels, &amp;c. what then? Muſt theſe downe in <hi>England</hi> therefore? 2. Perchance they had lands, but, as they complaine, they are taken away by Church-robbers. 3. The time and ſtate wherein they live, haply, will not ſo well bear it. But, 4. would not thoſe Churches accept of Lands, if time, the State, and Benefactors would afford it? And is thine eye evil in <hi>Scotland,</hi> becauſe God is good to us in <hi>England?</hi> The Commons in <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> live like Boors and Peaſants; and the Nobles in <hi>Ruſſia</hi> and <hi>Turkie,</hi> like ſlaves, and vaſſals. Hold you this a good Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, therefore it ſhould be no otherwiſe in <hi>England?</hi> We are no more bound in <hi>England</hi> to live without Lands, becauſe other Churches have none; then other Churches are bound to live upon lands, becauſe we have them: every Church or State, are in theſe caſes to be governed, and live by their owne Laws and Cuſtomes;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16.</note> and hitherto, God be praiſed, <hi>We have no ſuch Custome, no, nor all the Churches of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>13</label> Some have argued, that the Lands given to Biſhops in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> are held <hi>per Baroniam:</hi> which Baronies, with their Votes in Parliament, being taken away by an Act, the lands are, or may likewiſe be taken away.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> That they may likewiſe be taken away, as their Votes were in Parliament, or that by power they can be taken away, is not my diſpute; but, whether they may juſtly, and lawfully be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and ſold: and then to your Argument, (though it be out of my ſphere, ſo far as it is a title in Law) I ſubmit this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. Firſt, if that learned Antiquary, and diligent ſearcher of Hiſtorie and Records,<note place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſſar. ad ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum, Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on.</note> Sr <hi>Henry Spelman,</hi> informe me right, then it cannot hold, that all Biſhops in <hi>England</hi> hold their
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115963:25"/>lands by, or in the right of their Baronies; for he affirmes, that the title of Baron was not known in <hi>England,</hi> till the time of <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror; whereas moſt, I dare ſay of ſome Biſhops lands, were given, ſome one, ſome two, ſome three, ſome foure hundred years before the Conquerors time; and then judg, whether thoſe lands were given to hold <hi>per Baroniam!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, the ſame Author ſayes, that in <hi>England</hi> there were three ſorts of Barons; the firſt, who were made by <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, and theſe hold their Honors and Places in all Courts, by Preſcription, rather then by Tenure; and were therefore called, <hi>Barones Praeſcriptitii.</hi> The ſecond ſort were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Reſcriptitii,</hi> who, in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, were called by Writ to the Kings Courts. The third ſort called <hi>Diplomatici,</hi> who by the Kings Patents, were firſt created in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, and in that right had their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Now, can any ſay, but, that ever ſince there have been great Councils in <hi>England,</hi> the Biſhops had their places there, and ſo were to hold them by Preſcription, rather then by Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure? And if by the great Charter, the Rights and Liberties of the Church be inviolable, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſuch as rightly cannot be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; then this Right, Cuſtome, or Privilege, cannot juſtly be taken away. I conceive this true, that the two Kings, <hi>Williams,</hi> Father and Son, and after them King <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, out of ſpleen, ambition, or avarice, have impaired the firſt antient Dignity of Biſhops in <hi>England;</hi> and may have changed ſome of their Lands, to be held <hi>per Baro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iam,</hi> which at firſt were granted <hi>in puram &amp; perp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tuam El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emoſynam:</hi> Whereupon, Sr <hi>Henry Spelman</hi> cals the now Biſhops, <hi>Barones El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emoſynaries:</hi> yet doth it follow, that, if ſome have unjuſtly changed their Tenure, therefore, others more unjuſtly, may take away their Lands? Had it been ill in <hi>David</hi> to have cut off the lap of <hi>Sauls</hi> garment, might he therefore have killed the King?</p>
               <p>The caſe then, as I conceive it, is briefly this; The Saxon Kings, firſt chief Donors of much, if not of the moſt of the Biſhops Lands in <hi>England,</hi> gave, and confirmed them to be held, either in <hi>Franc-Almoigue,</hi> free from all Service, or for <hi>Divine Service,</hi> and they to hold them as Gods Almeſ-men and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115963:26"/>Servants; and this continued to King <hi>Edward the Confeſſor:</hi> after which time, ſome Kings, (how juſtly judg you) as Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors of this Land, altered the Tenure; making ſome, or moſt of their Lands (yet not all, for two are excepted, <hi>Carble</hi> and <hi>Rochoſter,</hi> ſo an antient Regiſter) to hold <hi>per Baroniam.</hi> After which, King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, whether moved in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, or upon ſome other good cauſes, reſtored the Lands to their antient juſt Rights, for his Charter could intend no leſſe to the Church, it looking back to the time of <hi>Edward the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor</hi> at leaſt. So that the Queſtion is, whether the Lands of Biſhops in <hi>England</hi> ſhould now hold <hi>per Baroniam,</hi> as changed by the Conqueror, or his Succeſſors, or as at firſt they were granted, and after reſtored by the great Charter, to their firſt Rights and Liberties,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Part Inſtit. p. <hi>94. 2.</hi> Inſtit. c. <hi>1.</hi> Ibid.</note> which was either in <hi>Franc-Almeigne,</hi> or for <hi>Divine Service.</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Edward Coke</hi> affirmes this later; and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith, <hi>By the great Charter, all the Rights are confirmed to the Church, and Church-men, which they had before, or at their firſt Grant.</hi> And in the ſame place more fully ſaith, <hi>The Church ſhall be fres,</hi> i. e. <hi>freed: By which,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>a reſtitution is graved of all ſuch Immunities, and Freedomes, as they enjoyed before, and to free them from all ſuch changes, as have been uſurped, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croached upon, by any power whatſoever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, I believe, that if the caſe were put concerning your own Lands, you would ſoon reſolve, that they ſhouldhold as by the firſt Donors grant, and after by the <hi>great Charter</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, rather then by that impoſition of a Conqueror. And why the ſame judgment ſhould not be given on Biſhope Lands, as on the Lands of other Free-men of <hi>England,</hi> I ſee not.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>14</label> But ſome, to take a ſhorter courſe, will perſwade, that to take and ſell theſe Lands of the Biſhops, is not Sacrilege; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theft is onely in things moveable, in which condition or acceptation, Lands cannot be underſtood.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Edward Coke</hi> cites the Canon Law, and approves of this, as agreeable to our Law, which ſaith, <hi>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> things are gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> to the Church,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2</hi> Instit. p. <hi>489.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>are holy Offerings, whether they beres</hi> ſolide, <hi>or</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biles, <hi>whether they be moveable or immoveable.</hi> Now doth our law ſay, there is no theft in things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> only ſaith it,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115963:26"/>theft is in moveables? If this, and not that, then why (for the honor of our Law, that it may not appeare to croſs Gods) may we not ſay, that our Law hath onely made <hi>theft</hi> in move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables puniſhable, becauſe it doth not conceive, how land, in the proper and ſtrict ſenſe of robbing, can be taken away and ſtoln? But, becauſe <hi>Sacrilege,</hi> or taking things immoveable, is not by our Law puniſhable, doth it therefore follow, that it is no ſin or puniſhable by Gods Law? Suppoſe we have no Law to puniſh an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> an <hi>Idoater,</hi> one that takes Gods Name in vaine, who prophanes the Lords day, who diſhonoureth his Parents, who tels or makes lies; are therefore, theſe no ſins, puniſhable by the Law of God? And that by Gods Law, defrauding God or man of immoveables, (be it of Lands) is a ſin; be pleaſed firſt to bethink your ſelf,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> King. 21.</note> whether King <hi>Ahah</hi> ſinned in taking away <hi>Naboths</hi> Vineyard, (an immoveable, I conceive, in your ſenſe and acceptation) and if he ſinned in this, then what Commandement brake he? Was it not the eighth, which ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale?</hi> And then doth it not plainly follow, that <hi>theft</hi> may be in immoveables? And that God may be robbed of immoveables, which is <hi>Sacrilege?</hi> And doth not God by his Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> ſpeaking, not only of Tithes and Offerings, but of the holy Lands, ſay,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 48.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhale not ſell, nor alienate them?</hi> which to doe, is Sacrilege.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>15</label> But, now followes the Argument, which will admit no Anſwer: There is a neceſſity lies upon the State to ſell the Biſhops Lands; for, without it, the publike debts cannot be paid: and without yeelding to this, the Church and State are in hazard to be utterly ruined; for till this be done, there will be no peace in the Land.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> Indeed, we ſay, neceſſity hath no law; and it is a ſad oaſe, that without, or againſt Law, divine, or humane, nedeſſity muſt ſweep all before it; but, before I anſwer fully, will you give me leave to ask you a Queſtion or two? 1. How, and by whom is this neceſſity brought on? 2. If not by Biſhops, but others, why not the Treſpaſſers (in ſtricter language the Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) to diſcharge the debt, rather then the Biſhops. 3. If this you will not yeeld to, yet why not ſome other way to be found, (which lawfully may be taken) rather then run this
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115963:27"/>courſe, which (as proved) is againſt Gods, and mans Law? I remember,<note place="margin">Mat. Pariſ.</note> it is ſtoried, that the Pope requiring great ſums of money from the Clergy, at which they repined, the Pope anſwered, that there was a neceſſity for it: Yet upon exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in a Councel in <hi>France,</hi> it was diſcovered, that the Pope had made, or brought on the neceſſity, and partly to that end, that he might fleece the Clergy; which that juſt Councel well weighing, put the holy Pope beſides his plot, and made him finde ſome other trickſom way, to ſalve his neceſſity. To anſwer therefore, if there be ſuch a juſt real debt, juſt it is, that it ſhould be ſatisfied; and as juſt, that they ſhould pay, who have cauſed the debt: if this be not li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, yet that the debt ſhould be diſcharged by a juſt and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal way, which I cannot ſee how it is, by ſelling the Biſhops lands, who were not the cauſes; but if they were, yet it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be juſt to take from God, what is his, for his Servants offence:<note place="margin">In anſwer to laſt Argument.</note> (of which, more anon.)</p>
               <p>That it will prove an hazard to the Church and State, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe theſe Lands be ſold, I conceive is an Argument, that lies either in the opinions, or wils of them, who other wayes may remedy it, if they wil; partly by finding the true proper cauſes of this miſchief, and neceſſity; or by levying the money by ſome general Tax on the whole Land, who ſo much groan under the preſent calamity, and oppreſſion, that, I perſwade my ſelf, they would rather pay that debt, then longer bear this burden.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe you cannot, or wil not find out any courſe, whereby to diſcharge the Publike debt, but this; then confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, how juſt and agreeable to Gods Word, this courſe is: and unleſſe you can ſhew, by Gods Law, that you may ſell theſe Lands, then, I dare affirme, that, be the neceſſity never ſo real, never ſo great, you may not ſell them to any end: In which caſe, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> is bold and peremptory, when he ſaith, <hi>Some affirm,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8.</note> 
                  <hi>that we ſay, Let us do evil that good may come whoſe damnation is juſt:</hi> juſt to them that ſay or teach ſo; and juſt to them who follow and practiſe ſo. Let me for your memory repeat that acts of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. <hi>57</hi>
                  </note> (the Heathen King, and a Tyrant) who would not in the greateſt neceſſity, which was of famine, yet
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115963:27"/>in that neceſſity he would not ſell the Prieſts Lands;<note place="margin">Annot, on the place.</note> and may we not feare a famine, or ſome other great plague to fall on thoſe Chriſtians, who ſhall dare doe contrary?</p>
               <p>And will you give me leave to add, and cloſe this with the Note of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Calvin? What bowels,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">On Acts <hi>4.35.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>What ſoules have we Chriſtians now a dayes? For the Primitive Chriſtians ſold their own lands, and laid the price at the Apoſtles feet, to relieve in time, and caſe of neceſſity; whereas we are not content alone</hi> maligne, <hi>like Malignants,</hi> (this was the ſenſe of the word then) <hi>to keep cloſe our own, but cruelly and unjuſtly we take away that which is other mens: they ſincerely, in faith, and a good conſcience, offered their own for the Publike neceſſity; but we uſe a thouſand pretexts, arts, and tricks fraudulently, and falſly, on all hands, and from all ſorts of men, to rake and draw to our ſelves other mens goods and eſtates.</hi> I beſeech you lay this to heart, and conſidering the too much truth of it at this time, what in you is, labour to correct and amend it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>16</label> The Biſhops have too much, which makes them proud, whereas, if they prove humble, they ſhall have portions or penſions for life; and this is as much as they can challenge by Gods Word.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> Juſt thus did ſome plead in the hurling times of K. <hi>Richard</hi> the Second,<note place="margin">Speed in R. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> (for ſo thoſe times were called) when many Peers and Commons, (not Ordained, it was not then come to this, but) Petitioned the King, that the Temporalties of the Church might be taken from the Eccleſiaſtical perſons, adding, that it were charity thereby to humble them. Whereupon, ſaith he, divers Parliament men deſigned among themſelves, out of which Religious Houſes each of them would have his ſhare. The King heard them, ſaith the ſtory, as I hope our King will, but yeelded not to their wicked projects. But if the Biſhops be not yet humbled enough, prove who thoſe proud ones be, in what, or how, and let thoſe proud ſuffer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law; for is it enough to ſay, ſuch an one is a Felon, and without more adoe, condemn him, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit his eſtate?</p>
               <p>And if it be ſaid, they have too much, have they any more, or have they ſo much as their firſt Donors, and Benefactors
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115963:28"/>gave them? and hold they it not by the ſame Law, by which all other Subjects hold their eſtates? I before told you, what the Levites held under the Law; and that God, who gave it them, thought not that too much, no not for them, who were but bodily labourers, as it were, in the Temple. And, if it may not offend to ask the queſtion, why in Gods name, may not a Scholar, as well born, as well deſcended, and as well, if not better bred, then others, who hath ſpent all his life time in the ſtudy of Humane and Divine knowledg, whereby to teach the people, and govern the Church; why may not he, I ſay, without envy, have and hold as much as a Lawyer, a Merchant, a mechanick Tradeſman? and leave for his wiſe and children thereby to live after him? For God held it juſt to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion the opulency of his Prieſts under the Law, to the wealth of the times, and the Land wherein they lived: yea, and that, if there were any exceeding, it was on the Prieſts behalf. I would you would be pleaſed to read two places of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.9, 10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6.</note> with the Notes of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Calvin, Bucer,</hi> and others; who obſerve, that Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in thoſe two places, made not a ſimple and bare compariſon, that, as the oxe, and the husbandman, lived by their labour, and had no more, ſo it ſhould be with the Miniſter. But, they ſay, there ſhould be a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable equity and equality in their maintenance; and this to be according to the dignity of their Function, and the quality of their work: and all this may be rightly evinced from thoſe Words of God himſelf,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 10.7.</note> 
                  <hi>The labourer is worthy of his bire.</hi> And who but an irreligious Atheiſt, or an ignorant Mechanick wil ſay, but, that the Study, the Function, the Work of a Biſhop, or Miniſter of the Goſpel, is ſequal to the beſt Lawyer, Merchant, or Tradeſmen? God forbid, that we ſhould be fallen into the times of <hi>Sylla,</hi> who baniſhed or ſold the beſt of the Romans, if they were rich?</p>
               <p>But, to return, if ſome one of that Order be rich and proud ſhal the Function be rooted out for the offence of the perſon? or, was this ever held agreeable to Religion, Law, Juſtice, or right Reaſon? There was a <hi>Judas,</hi> a Traytor, who carried the bag among the twelve Apoſtles of Chriſt, did Chriſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take away the Apoſtleſhip? Some Angels rebelled againſt
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115963:28"/>God, did God therefore deſtroy all the Angels, as Rebels? <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> would ſit one at the right, the other at the left hand of their Lord Chriſt; muſt all the Apoſtles therefore be deſpiſed, as proud, and uſurpers?</p>
               <p>And, to take away the Biſhops Lands, and give them a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is it not to take away their meat, and make them feed all on pottage? Or to deale with them, as ſome Idolaters, or <hi>Eli's</hi> ſons did, who took the fleſh, or beſt part of the Sacrifices to themſelves, and ſacrificed the bones or worſt to God? Or comes not this too neer our Engliſh Proverb, to ſteal a gooſe, and ſtick in place of it the feathers?</p>
               <p>And when it is ſaid, they ſhall have a ſitting maintenance, for that is all can be challenged from the Scripture; remember what Chriſt replied to thoſe, that murmured at the lord of the vineyards bounty, to ſome of the labourers more then others, <hi>Is thine eye evil, becauſe I am good?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.15.</note> Or repineſt thou at that which I have given to thoſe labourers, being it is <hi>lawful for me to doe with mine, what I wil?</hi> which holds right, both in the ſeveral Kings giving the Lands, and Gods accepting, and allowing them to his Miniſters.</p>
               <p>But, if we be to be pittanced by a competency, (as it is called) who, I pray, ſhall be the Steward, or Diſtributor? Shall he that robs the true man of his purſe, give back, what he thinks competent? And ſhall this be held juſt? If we underſtand, and beleeve the Prophet, it is God that is robbed, and who ſhall judge but God? Or what competency is fitting to be allowed to him? Is it one or two hundred pounds <hi>per Annum?</hi> If the beſt Interpreters, even of our modern Divines, may be heard, they will tell you from <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. that this maintenance muſt be honorable; and hath this been performed, when for two, three, foure yeares, you have taken all from them, and, yet not ſo much, as charging them with any offence againſt Law, or your own Ordinances? And is this Juſtice, or an honorable maintenance? Or would your Honors be content with the like?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>17</label> I have heard that, which I would rather truly call a Project then an Argument; that the Biſhops in <hi>England</hi> antiently had the Firſt-fruite, and Tenths of all the Spiritual livings in
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115963:29"/>every Dioceſe, which were the proper maintenance of thoſe Biſhops, and that therefore theſe might be reſtored to the Biſhops in lieu of the Lands, which by the Ordinance ſhould be taken from them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> To which, I muſt deſire you to know, that this Project or Device, is grounded upon a double miſtake: for, 1. the maintenance of Biſhops, ever ſince they were in <hi>England,</hi> was by lands, ſuch as were given them by their Royal Benefactors, and others. 2. The Biſhops in <hi>England</hi> held, or had not thoſe Firſt-fruits and Tenths, but the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> who under the falſe pretended Title of Univerſal Biſhop,<note place="margin">Mat. Pariſ. in H. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>849.</hi>
                  </note> uſurped, and took the ſame in <hi>England,</hi> (as he did almoſt, in moſt parts of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome beſides,) witneſſe that Grant of the Pope, who, <hi>De pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate ſibi à Deo conceſſâ,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pol. Virg. Hiſt. Angl. lib. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> gave thoſe Tenths for three years to K. <hi>Henry</hi> the Third. And the like of Pope <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban,</hi> who gave the Tenths in this Kingdome to K. <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, to aid him againſt <hi>Charles</hi> the French King, and thoſe that upheld <hi>Clement</hi> the Seventh againſt him: after which, they were paid to the Pope again, until they were reſtored to the Crown by K. <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2</hi> K. H. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> for that the King (as in that Statute he was ſtiled the Head of the Church, or) rightly is the Defender of the Faith, and Supreme Governor, in all cauſes, and over all perſons Eccleſiaſtical.</p>
               <p>Now then, if it might be juſt to grant the Biſhops theſe Firſt-fruits, and Tenths, in lieu of their Lands, yet what Juſtice can it be to rob (as we ſay) <hi>Peter,</hi> to pay <hi>Paul?</hi> to take that which is the Kings juſt right from him, thereby to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie for that, which is unjuſtly taken from God, and the Church? So, that as this Project failes in the ground, ſo in the ſuperſtructure too, it tends to a double Injuſtice; the one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King, and the other againſt the Church: and yet, if this could be done without Injuſtice to either, I know not how to clear the act from impiety, or Sacrilege; when God by his Prophet (as I before urged the Text) ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change that, which is holy to the Lord:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 48. <hi>Lev.</hi> 27.13.</note> Except (as it is excepted) for the Levite, and Prieſt, it may clearly appear, that the exchange be for the better, which this cannot be. Again, if by an Act theſe Lands, on theſe conditions, be now taken from the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115963:29"/>Church, then, by another Act of Reſumption or Reſtitution, thoſe Firſt-fruits and Tenths may be taken away from the Church again, and reſtored, as of right belonging to the Crown; and wherein then ſhall there be a maintenance for Biſhops in the Church?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum </seg>18</label> It hath been urged, (thereby to root out Epiſcopacy) that the King gives thoſe Biſhopricks, and ſo their Lands; and by theſe means, he holds the Biſhops at his beck, to ſay or do what he will.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> 'Tis true, that this was urged in Parliament, for taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Biſhops Votes there; which being done, why yet to take away their lands? for theſe have no Vote in Parliament. Or, why not to take away, as well, the lands of all thoſe, who hold by Office, Tenure, or Honor from the King? Yea, or from all thoſe, who make conſcience to keep Faith and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty? Or why not rather, on the other ſide, may ye not enact, that all Biſhops, who ſhall hereafter act, or aſſiſt againſt the Parliament, ſhall loſe their eſtates? which is as much as in Juſtice can be done. For, will you forbid all Wine, Knives, Swords, and the like? for theſe have, and may againe doe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief; and ſo have Parliaments too. But, God forbid, all theſe ſhould be taken away upon theſe grounds. I confeſſe, I have heard, that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Knox</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> counſelled after this manner, Pull down the Crows neſts, ſaid he, (for ſuch homely, or ſlovenly Similes they moſtly uſe, as beſt becoming them, and ſitting the palats of their Auditors) for elſe the black Birds will build againe: but of this counſel, ere he died, he repented, (though too late) for when the ſteed was ſtollen, he adviſed the Clergy, by word and pen, to gain-ſtand this black Sacrilegious act, of taking away the patrimony, and poſſeſſions of the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>19</label> But, we have bound our ſelves by an Oath, utterly to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate Epiſcopacy, root and branch; and to ſettle the right Government, according to Gods Word, and the beſt reformed Churches, which cannot be performed, without taking away the Biſhops foundation, on which they ſtand, their lands.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> If this Covenant were juſt and lawful, wherein they bind themſelves to extirpate Epiſcopacy; yet, it followes not, that
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115963:30"/>they have ſworn thereby, to ſell away the Biſhops Lands: for that theſe may better, and more juſtly, (as in the times of <hi>Edward</hi> the Second, <hi>Henry</hi> the Fifth, and <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth,) be converted to other uſes and ſervices in the Church. But grant, that they had expreſly, and directly ſworn, to have ſold theſe Lands, are they therefore, or thereby bound to doe it? unleſſe they can firſt prove, that by the Law of God and man, they might ſo doe? For otherwiſe, by the ſame reaſon or rule, <hi>Herod</hi> had been bound to have beheaded <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> and the Jews to have ſlain <hi>Paul,</hi> for each had ſworn and vowed thoſe bloudy acts. I doubt not, but your Aſſembly of Divines will teach you, that rather you ſhould repent, then proſecute the performance of an unjuſt or unrighteous Oath.</p>
               <p>And, what is urged, that after, and upon this Act, they have ſworn to ſettle a new Government, moſt agreeable to Gods Word, &amp;c. I verily beleeve, that thouſands, who have ſworn, neither did, nor yet doe underſtand, what in this they ſwore:<note place="margin">Jer. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> and how ſuch ſwearing agrees with that of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Thou ſhult ſwear in judgement,</hi> I cannot ſee; Lord have mercy upon them. For, 1. they ſwear poſitively to maintain the Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline, of the Church of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> and how many in <hi>England</hi> underſtand what the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline, of the Church of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> are?</p>
               <p>But, perchance, it will be anſwered, that they ſwear to <hi>defend them againſt our common enemies,</hi> for, ſo it is changed from the Scotiſh Copy, by our Aſſembly at <hi>Weſtminster:</hi> but, who are thoſe our enemies, againſt whom we are to maintain the Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline, of the Church of <hi>Scotland?</hi> Are they the Infidel, and Turk? for theſe are the Common enemies to Chriſt and his Goſpel. Or, be they the Arch-ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of mankind, the Devil? For who can be more properly our common enemy, then he, whom in our Baptiſm we all covenant to forſake, as our enemy? But, this common enemy in the Covenant, thus being left at large, for every man to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret or mean whom he will; is it not as much againſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or worſe, then that late decried [&amp;c.] in the laſt Canons? But, if ſome <hi>Oedipus</hi> will take upon him to expound theſe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115963:30"/>common enemies to be Papiſts, as ſome of the Aſſembly doe, 1. Who gives any one, or more, power to put a ſenſe upon a National Covenant, as this is called and pretended to be? 2. How can Papiſts, in common ſenſe, be called our common enemies, rather then the Devil, yea, or then Turk or Inſidel? For the Papiſts agree with us in the main fundamental points of our Creed; whereas the other three, the Turk, the Inſidel, the Devil, accord with us in none: and he is not ſo much our common enemy, who agrees in the maine, as he who dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers in all.</p>
               <p>And, is the Presbyterian Government proved by the Word of God? then, I pray, from what Text of Scripture, doe they confirm their Parochial, Claſſical, Provincial, National Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, which are the pillars, upon which, ſome ſay, Wiſdome hath placed her houſe? It is not, I hope, that <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.1. for there is mention of ſeven pillars. And, is this Government (as now ſetled or ſet forth) agreeable to the beſt Reformed Churches? But who muſt tell us, which theſe beſt Reformed Churches be? or muſt we pin our judgements and conſciences on other mens ſoules, who tell us, that the Scotiſh and French are thoſe beſt Reformed Churches? And were theſe the beſt, yet how can we ſettle our Government with theſe two, which differ one from another? Yea, and neither of them allow of any Appeal from their National Synod, in Eccleſiaſtical or Spiritual things; which this new Covenant, now held forth in <hi>England,</hi> doth? And yet, that Government of the Church, which hath continued in <hi>England,</hi> ever ſince Chriſtianity pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, (which is almoſt 1500. years) and wherein-nothing hath juſtly, or can be proved, to be in the eſſence and being of it, againſt the Word of God, muſt be aboliſhed, to bring that in, which neither agrees with the beſt Reformed Churches, nor can at all be proved by Gods Word.</p>
               <p>I pray, take this Note by the way, that the ſettling of the Presbyterian Government in <hi>Scotland,</hi> was the ſeditious, facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, tumultuous work, of four and twenty years; <hi>viz.</hi> from 1572. to 1596. And think on that of the Prophet,<note place="margin">Hoſ. <hi>10.4.</hi> De neceſ. reform. Eccleſ.</note> 
                  <hi>They have ſpoken words, ſwearing falſty, in making a Covenant:</hi> and at part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, hear Mr <hi>Calvin,</hi> writing to the Emperour, and Princes, in
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:115963:31"/>the Diet, or Parliament in <hi>Germany,</hi> and complaining of the Tyranny of the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> where of other Biſhops he ſpeakes thus, and in theſe very words; <hi>Talem nobis Hierarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ſi exhibeant, in quâ ſic emineant Epiſcopi, ut Chriſto ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe non recuſent, &amp; tum verò nullo non Anathemate dignos fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tear, ſi qui erunt, qui non cam reverenter, ſummâ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> obedientiâ obſervent.</hi> From which words it is plain, that Mr <hi>Calvin</hi> allowes, and approves of an Hierarchy, and Government in the Church by Biſhops; and not onely ſo, but, that he further profeſſeth, that all they, who doe not with all obedience re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and obſerve ſuch Biſhops, who ſubject themſelves to Chriſt, are worthy of the greateſt cenſure in the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>20</label> But, the ſucceſſes, and marvellous victories, which have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended this Parliament, are great, and manifeſt declarations, that God hath gone with, and guided the two Houſes in all their great Counſels, and Ordinances, whereof this is one, to aboliſh Epiſcopacy, and to ſell their Lands.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> Give me leave to anſwer by a Queſtion, or rather anſwer your ſelf in this Queſtion: becauſe <hi>Jehu</hi> thrived by killing his King, and rooting out his poſterity, doth God allow Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and Murther, and depoſing of Kings? Or ſhall we conclude, that the Pope, Mahomet, or the Turk, have been in the right, becauſe of their wonderful victories, and enlarging their Dominions? O the wretched, and moſt deceitful guile of the Devil! for who knowes not, both in Sacred, Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, and Prophane Hiſtories, that, as God often ſuffers his beſt and deareſt ſervants, to be troubled, perſecuted, and caſt down in this world; ſo he as often lets the tyrannous, proud, and ungodly, to exalt themſelves, that being left the more without excuſe, their condemnation might be the more juſt, and their puniſhment more grievous. And may it not be, that God may have a controverſie with you, and call you to an account for all your doings? And who knowes, whether this ſentence may not follow: <hi>I never knew you, depart from me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.23.</note> 
                  <hi>ye that worke iniquity,</hi> notwithſtanding all your victories?</p>
               <p>You may, perchance, blame my needleſs pains, in anſwering ſo many frivolous Arguments, and you may wonder too, who they be, who have framed ſuch ſimple Objections; but,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115963:31"/>you will ceaſe to wonder at this laſt, when you conſider, that, in theſe later times, the man hath been accounted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out zeal, or to want wit, that hath not ſomething to ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Biſhops; whom to vilifie, and ſlander, hath paſſed for an evidence of holineſſe: and, if you blame me in the former, I conteſſe, I had rather anſwer too much, thereby (if I could) to ſatisfie you in all, then to leave you unreſolved in any thing, though it be not material, nor worth the anſwering.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>21</label> Which this laſt Argument, I know, you will not hold to be, becauſe it reſts upon an Ordinance of the two Houſes; and therefore, I have kept it, as the Reſerve, and ſtrength of the whole hoſt of Arguments, for the laſt. Now the Ordinance thus ſpeaketh,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the aboliſhing of Archbiſhops, and Biſhops, and providing for the payment of the juſt and neceſſary debts of the Kingdome, into which, the ſame hath been drawn by a War, mainly promoted by, and in favour of the ſaid Archbiſhops, and Biſhops, and other their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, and dependents, Be it Ordained, that all their Lands be ſold, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                  </label> In which Ordinance, the ends wherefore theſe Lands muſt be ſold, are two, 1. For the aboliſhing of Epiſcopacy, a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which whether it be by Divine Right, beſides what hath been wrote by divers godly, reverend, and learned men, I deſire you to heare from a Treatiſe, in defence of Paedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſme, which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Charles Herle,</hi> Preſident of the Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Westminſter,</hi> by authority granted him by the two Houſes of Parliament, hath licenced, and which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly printed and publiſhed, 1645. where it thus ſpeaks.<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Mat. 28. <hi>gives a charge to the Apoſtles, which hath ſpecial reference to matters of Diſcipline, for the right Ordering and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Churches: And it is evident,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>by ſome paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in the New Teſtament, that ſome things were delivered to the Churches, and particularly to the Miniſters thereof, which were not then committed to writing, but were delivered from hand to hand, called therefore Traditions. And theſe Ordinances,</hi> ſaith he,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.15. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2.</note> 
                  <hi>ſet up and practiſed by the appointment of the Apoſtles, are equivalent in authority, to what Chriſt himſelfe hath immediately ordained. Hence therefore, is that,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.37. <hi>and hereupon,</hi> ſaith he,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115963:32"/>
                  <hi>the custome of the Church, which is eſtabliſhed, muſt stand for a Law, to quiet the conſcience of him, that is willing to be ſatisfied: as is proved,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.16.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What may appear to have been ordained by the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Pag <hi>8.</hi>
                     </note> and uſed by the Churches, even from the dayes of the Apoſtles, why ſhould it not be acknowledged, to be the commandement of Chriſt? But, you will ſay,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>how may it appear to have been the custome of the Churches ordained by the Apoſtles?</hi> to which himſelf anſwers, <hi>It is worth our obſervation, that the pattern and precedent, from whence moſt, if not all the cuſtomes in the Churches were taken, was the custome of Iſrael in the Old Testament. And this,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>may be one ſpecial reaſon, why the providence of God did not take ſo much care, for the writing of every cuſtome and ordinance, for the Government of the Church in the New Teſtament; becauſe the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent from whence they were taken, being at hand, if any alteration did creep in, it might eaſily be amended by reducing it to the pattern. Yea, who,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>can tell, whether the wiſdome of God, did not hereby provide to uphold the credit of the Church of Iſrael, againſt the frowardneſſe of ſome to diſeſteeme it. And that the Inſtitutions,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>of God by</hi> Moſes, <hi>for the Church of Iſrael, were the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern for the Apoſtolical Traditions, which were appointed for the Diſcipline, and Order to be obſerved, it will appear by divers particulars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>In the Old Teſtament, there was one day of ſeven ſet apart for holy reſt; in imitation whereof, the Apoſtles,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>by dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our bleſſed Saviour, conſecrated the firſt day of the week, called the Lords day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Iſrael had Synagogues beſides their Temple; and in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles times,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>there were places ſet apart called Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The directions,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>for Cenſures, were received from Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael; and that, not onely by the appointment of the Apoſtle,</hi> 1 Cor. 5. Tit. 3. <hi>but of Chriſt,</hi> Mat. 18.15.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>The liberty,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>which women take, to come to the Table of the Lord, muſt be acknowledged a Tradition of the Apoſtles, taken from the pattern of the Paſſeover.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>The cuſtome of the Apoſtles, to baptize the whole houſholds of them that beleeved, whence,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſhould they have it but from the pattern in the Old Teſtament?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:115963:32"/>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>The maintenance of Miniſtere,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Saint</hi> Paul <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes to be ordained of the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>in conformity to the Ordinance of the Old Teſtament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>So for Perſons, Iſrael had thoſe, who were ſet apart to the ſervice of the Altar and Temple; and accordingly,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ordained in ſeveral Churches, Elders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And whether,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Subordination of ſome in the Miniſtry, were not likewiſe an Apoſtolical Inſtitution appointed by Chriſt, and this alſo fetched from the pattern of</hi> Moſes, <hi>I diſpute not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He ſaith, he diſputes not, for what needs it any diſpute, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidering what he had proved before, and what he allegeth from Saint <hi>Hierom?</hi> the Father thus ſpeaks, <hi>That we may know,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ep. <hi>85.</hi> ad Evag.</note> 
                  <hi>that the Traditions of the Apostles were taken from the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, appears by this, that what</hi> Aaron, <hi>the Priests, and Levites, were in the Jewiſh Temple, the ſame, Biſhops, Preſbyters, and Deacons, doe rightly challenge in the Chriſtian Church.</hi> And that there was a Superiority, and Subordination among the Prieſts in the Old Teſtament, is ſo well known to all, that it needs no diſpute.</p>
               <p>The Author having laid down theſe grounds, concludes in theſe words: <hi>viz. Why this Rule ſhould hold in ſo many particulars, and onely faile in this point, I leave for them to give a reaſon, who know what difference is, betwixt reaſon and abſurdity; eſpecially, ſince it is plain by the teſtimony of the Antients, who lived in the next Ages after the Apoſtles, that this was a custome establiſhed by the Apoſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Author, anſwering an Argument,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>11</hi>
                  </note> drawn from <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.26. ſaith, <hi>The office of</hi> Moſes <hi>was to ſettle the Common-wealth, and National Church of Iſrael, by particular Lawes and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; where as the office of Christ was the reconciliation betwixt God and man, and the Redemption of mankind: and therefore, Chriſt loft it to his Apoſtles, and their ſucceſſors, in ſeveral ages, to provide for the welfare, and good of the Church in the New Teſtament;</hi> and thereupon, concludes all thus, <hi>What was inſtituted in the Old Testament, and is not repealed in the New, nor is incompatible with the ſtate of the Church in the New, that is underſtood, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, and commanded to the practice of the Chriſtian Church. Now, that an Hierarchy, or Superiority, and Subordination of the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:115963:33"/>Prieſts was inſtituted in the Old Testament, I think is denied by none, that understands the Government of that Church: and, that this kind of Government is repealed in the New Teſtament, appears not; for the words of Christ forbid onely an Heatheniſh Tyranny, and not a Chriſtianly Superiority, or an over-lording, and not an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly ruling.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 22.25, 26 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3.</note> 2. <hi>When in that place our Saviour explicitely forbids ſuch Dominion, or Lordſhip, as the Kings and Gentiles exerciſed, not ones mentioning, alluding to, or touching that Government, inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted and practiſed in the Old Testament; me thinkes it ſtands to reaſon, that this kind of Government by Superior and Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior, is rather confirmed then weakened by our Saviours prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition: for, had be intended the abolition of ſuch a Government, is it not probable, being now as it were upon the theme, that be would in ſome glance at leaſt, have ſtrook at that Superiority, and Subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation among the Jewes? Eſpecially, when you conſider what before was ſpoken, that the Apoſtles and their Succeſſors did, and were to order the Diſcipline, and Government of the Chriſtian Church, by the pattern of the Jewiſh: and, whether the like kind of Hierarchy was, or is likely to be incompatible for the Chriſtian Church, which was inſtituted for the Jewiſh Church, we may judge by the firſt, and after continued practice of the Chriſtian Church from the Apostles, and ſucceeding times.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here I ſhall cite, (whom you may as well credit, as you are willing to heare) Mr <hi>Calvin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Inſtit.</hi> 4.4.</note> who confeſſeth in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtian times, they choſe one called a Biſhop, who was as Conſul in <hi>Rome;</hi> and the Conſuls in <hi>Rome</hi> were above the Senators, in place, and power. And Mr <hi>Beza,</hi> and Mr <hi>Moulin</hi> come neerer to us and truth, who confeſſe, that either in, or very neer after the Apoſtles times, Biſhops ruled in the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church; where they deny not Biſhops, to have been in the Apoſtles times, onely they will not, leſt they ſhould offend or loſe by the truth, ſay what they did generally read, and I am perſwaded did beleeve, that Biſhops were in the Apoſtles times: yet in the other, they are plain and peremptory, ſaying, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops were ſoon after the Apoſtles; and could they have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it, they would as readily, and as plainly have ſaid, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops were not in the Apoſtles times but ſoon after; but by an artificial blinding or hood-winking the truth, they choſe
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:115963:33"/>rather to expreſſe it as they doe. Whereas <hi>Bucer,</hi> Profeſſor of Divinity in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> in K. <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth's time, ſpeaks as plainly, as truly, ſaying, From the firſt Ordination, and perpetual Inſtitution of Chriſtian Churches by the Apoſtles, it ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt, to have in them Biſhops: and in the Book of Conſecration of Biſhops, made, and ſet forth in the fifth and ſixth of K. <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Parliament, 8 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. it is thus ſaid, <hi>It is evident to all men, reading the Scriptures and ancient Authors, that from the Apoſtles times, there have been theſe Orders of Miniſters in the Church of Chriſt:</hi> viz. <hi>Biſhops, Preſbyters, and Deacons.</hi> And, if it were as evident, that the Apoſtles either inſtituted, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended a Presbyterian Government, and not Epiſcopal, may it not be as a wonder and aſtoniſhment, that ſo ſoon as ever the Apoſtles were deceaſed, or the moſt of them, the whole Chriſtian Church, diſperſed through the whole world, would ſuddenly conſpire, and convene to change that Government, inſtituted or commended by the Apoſtles, into Epiſcopacy? And that Epiſcopacie, and not Presbyterie, was the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, generally, I may ſay univerſally, uſed in the Chriſtian Churches, from the times of the Apoſtles, beſides the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties above mentioned, I appeale to all the beſt Hiſtories.</p>
               <p>Moreover, it cannot be denied, but that this Government came into this Kingdom, with the firſt planting of the Goſpel here, which was almoſt 1500. years agoe, and hath been ever ſince eſtabliſhed by our beſt Lawes, but hath been confeſſed by the beſt learned of the Aſſembly, not to be repugnant to Gods Word, and by the moſt learned and ſtrict Presbyterians, <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin, Beza, Monlin,</hi> acknowledged to be, either in, or ſoon after the Apoſtles times; and by the full conſent of the beſt Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians, proved to be inſtituted, if not by Chriſt, yet by his holy Apoſtles, and by, and from them, ſpread over all the Chriſtian world: and yet, to the end this holy Government may be aboliſhed, this deteſtable ſin of Sacrilege muſt be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. The end and the means we ſee meet, but then well weigh and conſider, that if it be damnation to him that doth ill to a good end, as the Apoſtle teſtifieth, then what damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall attend them, who to ſuch an end, as the aboliſhing
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:115963:34"/>ſo holy, or divine a Government as Epiſcopacy, ſhall wilfully commit ſo deteſtable a ſin as Sacrilege.</p>
               <p>But the ſecond end, perchance, is better; which is (as profeſſed) to pay neceſſary debts; a good end, I confeſſe, I would it were practiſed by all, yea, or in this caſe. But would not the Exciſe, and Compoſitions have diſcharged that debt, had the money been rightly imployed, as it was pretended? I pray, remember, that <hi>Charles Martell</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> under pretence of pay for the Holy War, ſeiſed on the Church Revenues, and though he promiſed reſtitution, yet was proclaimed by the beſt Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, to be a notorious, and a damnable Sacrilegiſt.</p>
               <p>But, how ever the ends meet, perchance, there is ſome great cauſe, that moved or provoked the two Houſes to this ſelling; yes, and the cauſe is expreſſed; for this late War was promoted by the Archbiſhops and Biſhops, and in favour of them, or their adherents, and dependents. I confeſſe, it ſeems ſtrange to me, that their Lands ſhould be ſold for what was done in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of them, who know not by whom this favour is done, neither are their favourers once impeached for the favourable act; for ſuppoſe one doe an evill act in favour of, or for M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Speakers ſake, who never deſired, nor acknowledged the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour; ſhall M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Speakers lands be ſold away for this? And yet more ſtrange it is, that their lands ſhould be ſold, becauſe the War was in favour of their adherents, and dependents.</p>
               <p>But, it is ſaid, that the Biſhops promoted this War; and yet not ſaid, who, nor when, nor how; but may not that more truly be ſaid, (which I would not add, were it not viſible and apparently known to all) that ſome one at the leaſt of the Biſhops, have ſtood with, and by the two Houſes in this War? For, hath there been wanting one, who hath ſought, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived dangerous wounds, (as it is reported and proclaimed) and that in the War for the two Houſes againſt the King? For which, he hath not only by ſuit, obtained a pardon for his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer diſſervice, (ſo called) but bath received thanks, and two thouſand pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> beſtowed upon him for his later ſervice? Doe Proteſtants, think you, maintain the Popiſh Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, <hi>remiſſâ culpâ remanet po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a,</hi> to puniſh after pardon? Yea, which is more, to puniſh after pardon, and reward? Or may
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:115963:34"/>not Gods example work ſomewhat for preſerving the Biſhops Lands, which did proclaim it ſelfe for the ſaving of all <hi>Sodom,</hi> that if but ten of ſo many thouſands, could be found for God, he would ſpare all thoſe thouſands grievous ſinners, for the ſakes of thoſe ten? Or did God, when ten could not be found, involve <hi>Lot,</hi> and his family in the general judgement of <hi>Sodom?</hi> And ſhall the Lands of that Biſhop, who hath deſerved ſo well of the two Houſes, be ſold with the reſt? for the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance concludes the ſale of all.</p>
               <p>If it be yet ſaid, (as what hath not been ſaid, no matter how untruly) that the late Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> promoted this laſt War; yet was it any part of the charge at his trial? And ſaith not our Law, <hi>for Treaſon of dead perſons not attainted or judged in their lives time,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">34 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.12.</note> 
                  <hi>their Lands ſhall not be impeached nor challenged?</hi> And if not their own, then, as I conceive, much leſſe ſhall the Lands be impeached which they held of the Church.</p>
               <p>But, I proceed, have all the Biſhops promoted this War? (which none yet with any ſhadow of truth hath ſaid, for ought I ever could hear) and if not, why, I pray, ſhall <hi>Robert</hi> be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for <hi>Richard?</hi> And if any of the Biſhops have promoted the War, have they been called, or ſuffered to anſwer the charge? And was it ever found agreeable to Juſtice, Law, or Reaſon, to give ſentence, before the party was heard, if he may be found? S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Edward Coke</hi> ſaith, it is againſt the Charter; nay,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2</hi> Inſtit. c. <hi>29.</hi>
                  </note> was the late Impeachment of the eleven Members, though by a ſpecial charge written, and profeſſed to be proved, I ſay, was this Impeachment Voted and Declared illegal, and unjuſtifiable, as to the ſuſpending their Votes, but for a time? And ſhal ſuch a general charge as this againſt the Biſhops, be held legal and ſufficient, for the ſelling away the Lands of all Biſhops in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> born and unborn, without ſummoning, hearing, or gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the charge againſt any? And, if upon trial, ſome Biſhop ſhall be found guilty according to Law, (which I preſume ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall be) yet ſhall the puniſhment of one, or more perſonal Delinquents, extend to others, who are innocent? Yea, to Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, which are not heirs at Law? Or ſhall the Lord of the Land, which is God, loſe his intereſt for the offence of his
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:115963:35"/>Aſſign or Tenent, which is the Biſhop? Or is this ſin in the Biſhops greater, then that vaſt damning original ſin in <hi>Adam,</hi> to condemn all, not onely that come of his ſeed and race, but all his Succeſſors, who are as little kin to his body or his ſoul, as to his offence? Nay yet, ſhall the inſenſate thing, that is, the Land, be prophaned, and let the pretended Delinquent, the Biſhop, goe unqueſtioned? which is, as if a Judge ſhould take away the Sword, and break it in pieces, becauſe it killed the man, but let the murtherer eſcape the while.</p>
               <p>The Charter ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> (<hi>Nullus liber homo, &amp;c.</hi>) that <hi>no Free man ſhall be amerced or puniſhed, but according to the quality of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence:</hi> and yet ſo, as with a <hi>ſalvo ſibi contenemento:</hi> where the Interpreter ſaith, this Free man extends to Biſhops, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding <hi>contenementum</hi> to be his countenance, ſaith, That, as the Biſhop is a Scholar, his books are his countenance; and as he is a man of holy Function, an honourable maintenance ſhould be his countenance: which if it might have held, then ſome Biſhop in this Land ſhould not have had, (not onely all his maintenance, Spiritual and Temporal, for theſe four years, utterly taken away, not allowing him in all this time one ſhilling, but not) his bedding, all houſhold-ſtuffe, and goods, yea, and all his books, not leaving him one; nor all, or any of theſe taken by the plunder of rude Souldiers, but by the Warrant of an honourable Committee, although without any Ordinance.</p>
               <p>The Charter goes on, and ſaith, That <hi>no Eccleſiaſtical perſon ſhall be amerced, or puniſhed, according to his Eccleſiaſtical, but to his Lay fee:</hi> whereas, here the clean contrary is publiſhed, and practiced by this Ordinance;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>od. <hi>32.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Aaron the high Prieſt made a gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Calf,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. <hi>28.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and built an Altar before it, and proclaimed a Feaſt for it, and ſaid, To morrow is a Feaſt to the Lord:</hi> for which abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable act,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> cauſed three thouſand men to be ſlain. <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welech</hi> the Prieſt, victualed and armed <hi>David</hi> againſt his King, for which act, <hi>Saul</hi> (the furious King) cauſed fourſcore and five of the Prieſts to be ſlain.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 1.7. 1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 2.26.</note> And K. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid to <hi>Abiathar</hi> the Prieſt, who <hi>had helped Adonijah</hi> to be King againſt <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Thou art worthy of death.</hi> I could inſtance in many more acts of theſe Prieſts, moſt diſpleaſing to their Kings, and ſome
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:115963:35"/>really ſinful before God; yet doe we find that any went about for all theſe acts, to deprive the Prieſts of their Lands, and maintenance for ever? Might I not put you in mind, that we have had in the time of Popery, a <hi>Becket,</hi> a <hi>Langton</hi> a <hi>Wolſey,</hi> and other Biſhops, who inſtigated by the blind falſe Principles of their Religion, have fallen into groſſe treaſonable acts? yet did the King, and the two Houſes for their offences, ſell away the Lands of the Church which they held? I read, in the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, that the Jewes in <hi>England</hi> were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to pay the third part of their eſtates,<note place="margin">Mat. Par. p. <hi>489</hi>
                  </note> that they might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy their peace; but muſt Biſhops be worſe uſed by Chriſtians, and their Countrey-men (contrary to all Law) then Jews?</p>
               <p>And may not the Biſhops truly ſay, what the eleven Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers give for their Anſwer in their printed Papers: <hi>viz.</hi> We muſt be removed, and that we may ſo be, we muſt be repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be what we are not; and what ever is amiſſe in the Kingdom, we are made the cauſe, and muſt bear the blame of it. <hi>Christianos adignem:</hi> what publike calamity ſoever befell in the Primitive Perſecutions, the poor Chriſtians were ſaid to be the cauſe, and muſt be made the expiatory Sacrifice for all. But let men ſay what they will, <hi>Elijah</hi> the Prophet of God, was never the more the troubler of the Kingdom, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was called ſo; and therefore, we will ſay as <hi>Job,</hi> Our witneſſe is in heaven, and our record is on high. Thus far they, and ſo the Biſhops.</p>
               <p>But, for the cloſe of all, ſuppoſing the Biſhops were, what is here or elſewhere unjuſtly charged upon them; yet give me leave to put you a Scripture caſe, and Gods judgement there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, and I ſhall leave it to your judgment and conſcience to make the Application: the caſe is ſet down, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. where three ringleaders, and a hundred and fifty choſen men, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſeducers of the people, (malignants theſe indeed, for they) rebelled againſt the Prince, whom God had ſet over them, and raiſed a deſtructive Schiſin againſt the high Prieſt, and his Succeſſors, utterly to extirpate them; in this caſe, God will not ſuddenly condemn, without examination of cauſe and perſons, though he knew both, (as, neither would Chriſt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:115963:36"/>caſt out <hi>Judas,</hi> a thief, and a traitor, becauſe, as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> notes, he was not ſo convict, according to the Law) but God, to let the malignants have a fair, open, and juſt trial, bids them bring their cenſers before him, and there to have the cauſe fully examined: whereupon, God found thoſe mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guants to be the offenders; and, although the cenſers were uſed by them in the maintenance of this Rebellion and Schiſm, yet, what doth God? Doth he let the perſons goe free, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence onely the cenſers to be ſold, and turned to pots and the like, for the ſervice of the Common-wealth and State? No, quite contrary, he puniſhed the malignants with an unheard of fearfull kind of death; but the cenſers of theſe ſinners, <hi>Make them plates for the Altar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. <hi>38.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>for,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>they were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered before the Lord, therefore, they are hallowed.</hi> What then ſhall we ſay to this? Is Gods judgment unrighteous, to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the malignants, and ſpare the thing offered before the Lord? Or, is yours juſt, to ſentence and ſell the thing offered before the Lord, and let the malignants (ſo called) goe free? Or, why judge ye not according to Gods judgement, O ye ſons of men?</p>
               <p>A wiſe, and great Peer of this Realm, ſpake truly well in this Parliament, when he ſaid, That a Law, or Ordinance, when it is made, (according to the juſt power of it) binds to obedience: But, ſaith he, it follows not therefore, that this Law or Ordinance is good, and juſt, for that the beſt, and wiſeſt Law-makers of men, have been found to blame in this kind; for ſo I read, <hi>Solon</hi> made one Law to aboliſh all debts, whereby the honeſt creditors loſt, and the falſe debters gained. Another Law he made to puniſh all Neutrals in time of Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which <hi>Plutarch</hi> condemned, For, ſaith he, this is to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the ſound party, which might otherwiſe ſtrengthen the weak. <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> without reſpect to Religion, Juſtice, or Temperance, (a Policy too much uſed now adayes) made Laws onely to breed and encourage Souldiers, whereby the Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonians continued ſo long, as their Wars held, and no longer. I could give inſtance in Laws and Ordinances neerer home; but I forbear, and cloſe with that counſel of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:115963:36"/>Prove all things, hold fast that which is good:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.21.</note> for all things are not good, and juſt, onely on this ground, becauſe they are Laws and Ordinances.</p>
               <p>Some more there are to be found in the common Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, which I know not what to call; Objections, if you will; for they doe not deſerve the name of Arguments: yet this, in regard that it ſeems ſo plauſible, and is ſo much cryed up by the back friends of the Church, and her Revenues, I could not but take notice of, and labour to ſatisfie the judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and reaſonable. This, what you will, runs thus,</p>
               <p>The Lands were given to the Biſhops for their Preaching; and therefore they, not performing this ſervice, ought to loſe the benefit, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Lands.</p>
               <p>Although, I cannot but approve of that, as prudent, (and the rather, becauſe obſerved and practiſed by all beſt States, untill within theſe laſt hundred years, it hath been altered by Factious and Rebellious people) that, among all Religions, true and falſe, they have made, and held a diſtinction of Prieſts; giving to ſome more honour and maintenance, then to the reſt: Yet, I muſt, and doe, with all reverence, ſubmit to that of Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi> ſaying, That a man dignified without merit, is like ſmoak in an high candle-ſtick; and that a man in high place, not able to govern, is like an ape on the top of an houſe: and therefore, as the <hi>Labourer is worthy of his hire,</hi> ſo an honourable maintenance doth require a worthy Labourer. Now, in this caſe, what is the labour of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, becomes the Queſtion.</p>
               <p>To which, the Arguers againſt Biſhops, (or rather againſt their Lands) ſeem to ſay; Preaching is that their work or labour.</p>
               <p>But, then let me propound three other Queſtions, 1. What is meant by Preaching. 2. Whether Preaching alone be the Biſhops work. 3. Whether, not withall, (or not more ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) the well ordering, or governing the Church be his work.</p>
               <p>And, that I may clear the laſt Queſtion firſt; conſider, I pray, when Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in two places: <hi>viz.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor,</hi> 12.28. and <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11. had ſet down both the extraordinary, temporary, and perpetual ordinary Officers of the Church; that, of the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:115963:37"/>later ſort, he mentions onely two, <hi>Governments and Teachers,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. and <hi>Paſtors and Teachers, Epheſ.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Now, if the Governor and Paſtor, in theſe places be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from Teacher, then, I hope, it is evident, that Preaching alone is not the office, or work of a Biſhop, as ſome would have it.</p>
               <p>And, that they are diſtinct, it may be conceived, for, that the other Officers mentioned in thoſe places; as, Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts, are diſtinguiſhed one from the other; and therefore, probably, theſe two, Governors or Paſtors, and Teachers, ought, or may likewiſe meane two ſeveral works.</p>
               <p>And, when Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in each place, ſaith, <hi>God gave,</hi> and <hi>God ſet theſe in the Church;</hi> in that he gives them ſeveral names and titles? why may we not conceive, that under the diſtinct names, the works likewiſe are to be diſtinguiſhed?</p>
               <p>And, that Paſtor, in Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> may be the ſame with Governor, I appeal to Saint <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, who <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. ſending for, (not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as he terms them to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> but) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Elders of the Church, in his charge to them, uſeth not the metaphor of a School-maſter, or Teacher, but of a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard; and therefore begins, <hi>Take care to the flock.</hi> And what is he to doe in that care? why, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to feed the Church: And may not he be rightly ſaid, to take care of, and to feed a flock, that ſo overſees them, as that they may be well ordered and fed? And for this, the Apoſtle cals not theſe El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Teachers, but, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Overſeers, or truly Biſhops.</p>
               <p>And doth not the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.7. call this Biſhop or Governor in the Church, by an other like name, when he terms him <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Steward? And in what conſiſts the duty or office of a Steward, but in this, that, as a Biſhop, a Shepheard, a Governor, he take care, and ſo order it, that the family may have their ſeveral allowances; and be wiſely, and rightly governed, by exhortation, admonition, and if need be, by caſting out?</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:115963:37"/>
               <p>And from theſe Texts, or (if you pleaſe more plainly, without any borrowed ſpeech) from that <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. <hi>verſe</hi> 6. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> having premiſed, that <hi>in the Miniſterie there are divers gifts;</hi> he ſubjoyns, <hi>Let him that teacheth, wait on teaching, Ver.</hi> 7. and <hi>he that ruleth, let him doe it with diligence.</hi> And from that, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. in the 1. Verſe, having ſpoke of <hi>the office of a Biſhop,</hi> he adds Ver. 4. <hi>He must be one that ruleth well:</hi> For, ſaith he, Ver. 5. <hi>If he know not how to rule his own houſe, how ſhall he take care of the Church of God?</hi> Which phraſe, <hi>[taking care of the Church]</hi> both in this place, and that <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. muſt ſignifie a ruling, or governing of the Church, and flock of God. I ſay, from theſe ſeveral Texts, it will plainly appear, that the office of the Biſhop conſiſts not <hi>alone</hi> in preaching to, but in governing the Church.</p>
               <p>And, here I may conceive, that the <hi>office,</hi> or <hi>work</hi> of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop in this, differs not much from that which is practiſed among Souldiers, Sea men, and others, who, after much time and pains ſpent in the inferior places, at laſt, partly as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of their former ſervice, but eſpecially, for their great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, and authority gained, are advanced to higher places; wherein they rather ſtand, ſit, or ride, to direct, guide, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern others under them, then to work and labour, as they did before. And ſeeing the Levites, Souldiers, and almoſt all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions have a time, when, having ſpent their beſt ſtrength, and arriving to the age of fifty or fixty years, they are <hi>emeriti,</hi> and freed from their former kind of labour; yet muſt the Biſhop only of all others, be deprived of this ſo juſt a grace and benefit?</p>
               <p>But ſithence that no compaſſion can be ſhewed to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, from men, let us ſee whether from the holy Text ſome indulgence may not be found; and to this purpoſe, let us exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine what it is, in Scripture-underſtanding, to Preach. Now, the word in the holy Goſpel, which we tranſlate to preach, is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; which is ſpoken of Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Jeſus began</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to preach.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.7.</note> And when Jeſus had ſent abroad his twelve Apoſtles, his Commiſſion is in the ſame word, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>preach;</hi> and the ſame word Saint <hi>Paul</hi> uſeth moſt frequently, and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome any other, to this ſenſe. And, that Teaching, and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:115963:38"/>Preaching are, and ſignifie the ſame thing, ſee <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.1. where it is ſaid, that <hi>Jeſus departed,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to teach and to preach;</hi> and from the ſeveral Texts, where this word is found, it will eaſily appear, that to preach the Word, in the Goſpels and Epiſtles ſenſe, is to declare, and make known the Doctrine, the means, and the way to faith and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, whether by word, or by writing; whether privately, or publikely; though the Preacher never goe up into a pulpit, or desk, there to expound ſome place of Scripture: for, if Preaching conſiſted in this, and not in that, how can we prove that Chriſt or the Apoſtles did ſo frequently preach?</p>
               <p>And, now that the Biſhops in <hi>England,</hi> ſince the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, have, according to the right ſenſe of the word, been Preachers, I appeal to a learned Judge, and unpartial witneſſe, Doctor <hi>Moulin,</hi> (the famous Presbyterian in the Church of <hi>France</hi>) who, in his third Epiſtle to that pious, and moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Biſhop <hi>Andrewes,</hi> thus writes, <hi>I very well know that the Reformation of the Church in England, and the ejection of Popery, next to God and your Prinees, is chiefly to be aſcribed to the learning and induſtry of your Biſhops.</hi> And, have we not beſide our own knowledg, (if envy or malice will ſuffer us to ſpeak what we know) the teſtimony of forain, godly, and learned men, who have openly avouched the Sermons, and writings of our late and preſent Biſhops in <hi>England,</hi> to be anſwerable, in worth, if not preferred before the moſt of any in other Countries?</p>
               <p>And, can it be denied, that the moſt of the preſent living Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in <hi>England,</hi> did often preach, (even in that ſenſe as you take Preaching) untill they were, as of late, either directly hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, or elſe not ſuffered to preach, unleſſe they would take the new Covenant? which if they ſhould do, they might truly uſe the words of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.27.</note> 
                  <hi>While we preach unto others, we our ſelves are become caſt-awayes, i. e.</hi> doubt of our ſalvation, or to be rejected.</p>
               <p>But, if the Biſhops caſe be ſuch, that they muſt be caſt away, becauſe they doe not write or preach, (as is objected) then, I pray, let me ask how many Sermons have ſome of the Aſſembly of Divines (in <hi>England</hi>) preached, within theſe four
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:115963:38"/>or five years laſt paſt? And I dare affirm, they are not ſo many, as moſt of the Biſhops uſually did preach before the time of their ſuſpenſion, or perſecution. And, though the number of the Aſſembly of thoſe Divines, three times exceeds this of the Biſhops living; yet have there ſo many of them wrote, and confuted him, whom in their Covenant they ſtile the common Enemy, as there be of the Biſhops yet living who have?</p>
               <p>Laſtly, have theſe Divines (in the Aſſembly) preached or wrote much, except it were to deſtroy, what was lawfully eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, and thereby to raiſe themſelves into power, mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and authority?</p>
               <p>But, to end this Anſwer, If the Biſhops Lands muſt be ſold, becauſe they preach not, then, either this is but a pretence and excuſe of iniquity, or elſe none but Preachers muſt have and enjoy them: and, if none but Preachers muſt have them, and yet they muſt be ſold for a great price, then, I fay, either the Presbyterian Preacher, is grown very rich in theſe later times, or elſe none but the Lay-Independent can purchaſe and have them. For the Independent in Orders, profeſſeth himſelf, like ſome Orders of Friers, to live on alms, or the charity of others, and therefore he is not able to make ſuch a purchaſe; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it muſt come to paſſe, that the Lay-Independent muſt prove the Chapman, being that he alone hath money enough, and hath withall obtained the Grace to be a Preacher. And, if theſe can gain ſo much by their preaching, I cannot but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend their wit, while in the mean time I ſmile at the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians folly, who hath ſo many years been beating the buſh, till another, as it were out of a buſh, doth catch the bird.</p>
               <p>For a cloſe, I pray, keep this in mind, that if the Biſhops muſt loſe their Lands, becauſe they are not conſtant Preachers, then, by the ſame reaſon, none but conſtant Preachers ought to hold thoſe Lands.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:115963:39"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> The Curſes, and puniſhments, which are ſet down, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted in Holy Writ againſt Sacrilegious Alienations, are held forth and opened.</head>
               <p>IF your patience would ſuffer it, I could, by way of an addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, fill much paper with the direful curſes, and ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequents, if not effects thereof, upon the ſeveral Invaders of Church-Lands within this Kingdom; who might have uſed the like Eſcutchion and Motto, which <hi>Julian,</hi> that Apoſtate Perſecutor, and Enemy of our Lord Chriſt had; which was an Eagle ſtruck with an arrow, feathered from the Eagles own wings,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.9.</note> and had this word, <hi>Propriis configimur alis:</hi> which in the Prophets words is, <hi>Perditio tua ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te, Thou hast destroyed thy ſelf.</hi> But other better pens have ſaved me this labour.</p>
               <p>Therefore, that Curſes may be uſed and in this caſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult, I pray,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.17.</note> with that of <hi>Moſes, Curſed be he that removes his neighbours Land-Mark, and all the people ſhall ſay Amen.</hi> Now, if a curſe may be pronounced againſt him that removes the mark of any neighbours Lands, then much more againſt him who removes the mark of God, or his Miniſters. 2. If, for removing the mark, whereby the bounds might be known, then, why not for taking and ſelling them away, that they be no more ſeen to be the Miniſters?</p>
               <p>And, though we are apt to tranſlate the deaths, and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Sacrilegious perſons, to other cauſes then to Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege; yet it is a general certain Rule, <hi>Innatum eſt ſceleri ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicium ſceleris:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.12.</note> and therefore it is ſaid, <hi>God will be as a moth and rottenneſſe, i. e.</hi> the puniſhment that God inflicts on ſin, ſhall be as a moth to cloth, and rottenneſſe to the tree, or body of man. Now, whence comes the moth that deſtroyes the cloth, but out of duſt and filth that lay hid in the cloth? And whence rottenneſſe to deſtroy the plant, or body of man or beaſt, but out of the moiſture and corrupt humors in the ſame body, which is by it deſtroyed? The Sacrilegious man in
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:115963:39"/>himſelf, or poſterity periſheth. Say not then, it was his want of providence, it was his ſuretiſhip, or the like; no, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege was the moth, or rottenneſſe: for, as <hi>Solomon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 20.25.</note> 
                  <hi>It is a ſnare.</hi> Yea, but ſay ſome, the ſnare doth not overtake, or not preſently; ſo neither doth the moth, nor rottenneſſe: but know, that as the moth, ſo the ſnare, it makes no noiſe, that men may hear and take warning; and ſo divine Juſtice winks when it ſleeps not, and kils while we ſleep, or little think of it. But be ſure that the ſnare, which God ſets as a trap to catch the Sacrilegious perſon, he ſo ſets it, that firſt or laſt it ſhall take hold; and, as the man devoured holy things, ſo ſhall this ſnare deſtroy the devourer. And, that we may fear to fall into this ſnare, hear, I pray, what God hath threatned, and executed upon tranſgreſſors in this kind; and I think be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand, I may ſay, and ſay truly, that more, and more heavy curſes and plagues, have not been recorded in holy Writ, to have been inflicted upon any ſin, then on this of Sacrilege.</p>
               <p>I ſhall orderly proceed, as I find them laid down in Gods Word, yet omitting many inſtances, and examples, though pertinent to my purpoſe, onely for brevity ſake. And firſt, when <hi>Moſes,</hi> in Gods ſtead, bleſſed the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. <hi>33.</hi>
                  </note> (Gods Miniſters in his holy Service) he did it in theſe words, <hi>Lord bleſſe his ſubstance, and accept of the work of his hands:</hi> and then immediately followes the curſe upon all that ſhall attempt to ſpoile or hurt them;<note place="margin">Ver. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>And Lord ſmite through the laynes of all that riſe againſt him, and of them that hate him, that they riſe not againe.</hi> This was firſt denounced by <hi>Moſes</hi> their firſt Prince, and ſee how ſoon this begins to work; for in the next Princes time, when <hi>Achan,</hi> in war, had gained, and privately kept that wedge of gold, which was due to have been dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to God, all Iſrael ſmarts for it:<note place="margin">Joſh <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> for this they were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfited by their enemies, until the Sacrilegious perſon <hi>Achan</hi> was put to death, and an atonement made by all to pacifie Gods wrath.</p>
               <p>The Jewes are carried away captives by the Chaldeans,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.14, 17.</note> as a puniſhment of their prophanation of the Temple, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Prieſts; each of them being branches of Sacrilege.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:115963:40"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solomon,</hi> the wiſeſt earthly King, being counſelled (as the moſt learned conjecture) to make uſe of what his Father had laid up toward the building of the Temple, anſwers, No; for ſayes he,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 20.25.</note> 
                  <hi>It is a ſnare to devour holy things:</hi> in which metaphor, the poſſeſſions of the Church ſeem to be the corn or bait, and the Devil to be the hunter who holds the ſnare, wherewith he entangleth the Church-robber to deſtroy him.</p>
               <p>Neither did <hi>Solomon,</hi> the Type of Chriſt, alone pronounce this ſentence; but <hi>Darius,</hi> an Heathen King, when, in favour of the Jewes, he dedicated the building of a Temple to their God, ſets this curſe upon the invaders, ſpoilers, or robbers thereof:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezra</hi> 6.12.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord deſtroy all Kings, and people,</hi> (not any one or other, but both) <hi>who ſhall put their hands to alter, and to destroy this Houſe of God, which is at Jeruſalem:</hi> and whether God ſaid Amen to this Prayer of <hi>Darius,</hi> judg ye, by what happened to <hi>Antiochus, Nicanor, Craſſus,</hi> all whom, as they were robbers, and prophaners of that Temple, ſo the goods thereof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſnares for their deſtruction.</p>
               <p>And this accords with that of the Prophet <hi>Jeremy, Who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour things holy to the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.3.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall offend, and evil ſhall come upon them, ſaith the Lord:</hi> and ſee how ſoon this Prophecy was ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, for <hi>Jehoiakim</hi> the King takes the Cedar out of Gods Houſe,<note place="margin">Jer. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> (he takes not all the Lands, and perpetual maintenance of all the Prieſts, but) he takes onely the Cedar out of Gods Houſe, wherewith he ſieled his own windows, (he ſold it not) but ſieled his own windows with it; hear the judgement, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoiakim ſhall be buried like an Aſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and ſhall be caſt out beyond the gates of Jeruſalem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. c <hi>1.</hi> &amp; <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> After this, <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> robs Gods Houſe of the gold and ſilver veſſels therein; what followes? He lives with,<note place="margin">Dan. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> and lives a Beaſt ſeven years; and <hi>Belſhazzor</hi> his ſon, for prophaning thoſe veſſels which <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> his Father had taken away, came to a ſudden end; the Empire is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from him, his race, and poſterity for ever.</p>
               <p>Neither doth this Curſe and Snare reach and deſtroy indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduals alone, but it lights on the whole Land, where the ſin is committed; we found it before in the puniſhment of <hi>Achans Sacrilege,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> and now we may ſee as much expreſſed by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:115963:40"/>
                  <hi>Malachi,</hi> who tels the people, that, for robbing God of what was offered to him,<note place="margin">Ver. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ye are curſed with a curſe, i. e.</hi> ye are certainly and heavily curſed. And <hi>ye are curſed, even ye, the whole land;</hi> and that curſe no leſſe, then the moſt dreadfull to nature, with the curſe of a general, and great famine. And ſee how God proportions his puniſhment, even to the nature of the ſin; for in <hi>Joſhua's</hi> time, the people for <hi>Sacrilege</hi> committed in war, is puniſhed in war by the ſword of the enemy: and here in <hi>Malachi,</hi> they have robbed the Prieſts of their maintenance and bread, and themſelves are therefore puniſhed, and ready to ſtarve for want of bread; where me thinks the Prophet tacit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gives a reaſon for this ſeverity, when he ſaith, Will a man rob his God? God his Maker, his Preſerver, his Redeemer? Will he be ſo ungracious? ſo unnatural? Yea, and will he rob that God, who we beleeve is coming to be our Judge? Will he be ſo audacious? For if this Judge will caſt the unmerciful into hell, becauſe they relieved not the poor; what torments ſhall be prepared for them, who ſo ungraciouſly, ſo unnaturally, ſo audaciouſly have robbed God their Father, their Saviour, and their Judge?</p>
               <p>Will you have a more full view together of Gods anger and wrath againſt this ſin? You ſhall find it in two ſeveral Pſalms, in one,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. <hi>&amp;</hi> 83. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. <hi>v.</hi> 4, 5, 12, 19, 20, 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. you ſhall hear God ſix times call <hi>Sacrilegious men</hi> his open, and profeſſed enemies, and adverſaries; and that he called them ſo for this ſin, read Ver. 4. of that Pſalm, where the cauſe of thoſe termes is couched,<note place="margin">Ver. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>For thine enemies roar in the midſt of the Congregation, and have ſet up their Banners for ſignes:</hi> and what the fuller ſenſe of thoſe words are, ſee anon after, <hi>They have defiled, or prophaned,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>the dwelling place of thy Name, i. e.</hi> the Temple or Church: and yet they ſtick not here, who begin here, and therefore goe on, and ſee further, <hi>They have ſaid in their hearts, Let us deſtroy them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>i.e.</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. And, will you know how they will deſtroy the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets? then caſt your eye on the other fore-cited <hi>Pſalm</hi> 83.3. where it is ſaid, <hi>They have taken crafty counſell;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>83.3.</hi> Ver. <hi>9.</hi> &amp; Ver. <hi>5</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and they have ſaid, Come, let us cut them off from being any more:</hi> (here is root and branch) <hi>yea, they have conſulted together with one conſent,</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:115963:41"/>yet more, <hi>they are confederate,</hi> or covenanted, with whom? <hi>Aſſur alſo</hi> (out of the North) <hi>is joyned with them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> But, by what means ſhall theſe Prophets of God be rooted out, after all conſulting and covenanting?<note place="margin">Ver. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> That is alſo expreſſed, <hi>Let us take the Houſes and Inheritances of God in poſſeſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You have heard the firſt part of this Pſalm, which our laſt Tranſlators call Gods complaint againſt the conſpirators a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Church; and the ſecond part of the Pſalm, they term a Prayer, Imprecation, or Curſe, if you will, againſt thoſe conſpirators and enemies; where the Prophet ſpeaks thus, <hi>Ariſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74.22.</note> 
                  <hi>O Godplead, thou thine own cauſe:</hi> as though God had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got his Church, and had been too long ſilent in his own cauſe; and, in pleading, <hi>Remember, how the folliſh man blaſphemeth thee.</hi> The Sacrilegious man, in Gods and the Prophets ſenſe, is but a Fool, firſt or laſt he will prove ſo; and ſuch a Fool, who, by robbing God, whom the world may hereby think (as <hi>Plato</hi> called God on this occaſion) a tame idle God, to ſee himſelf robbed, and not right himſelf; by this, ſaith the Pſalmiſt here, cauſeth God to be blaſphemed, and ill ſpoken of, and is therein himſelf the Fool.<note place="margin">Ver. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> The Prophet goes on, <hi>O Lord, forget not the voyce, i.e.</hi> the counſels and votes, <hi>of thine enemies: for the tumult of thoſe that riſe up againſt thee encreaſeth,</hi> or aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth up to heaven, <hi>more and more.</hi> Again, <hi>remember:</hi> which remembrance in this place imports, 1. to puniſh, 2. with an eternal puniſhment, never forget it, O Lord; 3. In this 74. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> being of little more then three times ſeven Verſes, yet in theſe, the Prophet cals to God ſeven times, to remember, and not forget to puniſh thoſe enemies; the like to which I doe not remember, in any the like ſcantling of Scripture. And, 4. he haſtens,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ver.</hi> 3. <hi>Ver.</hi> 10, <hi>&amp;</hi> 11. <hi>V.</hi> 20. <hi>V.</hi> 12.13 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.12.</note> or ſpurs up God; <hi>Life up thy feet,</hi> and then, <hi>uſque que?</hi> and again, <hi>quouſque?</hi> 5. He adjures God to it, by putting him in mind of his Covenant, and what-he had done. 6. Will you be pleaſed to take one Note more, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. the Prophet cals to God ſeven times, not to forget to puniſh theſe ſinners; ſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79. <hi>Ver.</hi> 12. he prayes God to <hi>render ſeven-fold into the boſomes</hi> of ſuch ſinners: and then <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83. ſee accordingly a ſeven-fold puniſhment inflicted upon them. 1. <hi>O Lord, do unto
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:115963:41"/>theſe thine enemies, as thou diddest unto the Midianites,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>V.</hi> 9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10. <hi>V.</hi> 11. <hi>V.</hi> 13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.</note> 
                  <hi>which pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed, and became as the dung of the earth.</hi> 2. <hi>Make their Nobles like Oreb and Zeb,</hi> (both ſlain) <hi>who ſaid, Let us take to our ſelves the Houſes and Inheritances of God in poſſeſſion.</hi> 3. <hi>Make them, O Lord, as a wheel, and as the ſtubble before the wind.</hi> 4. <hi>As the fire burneth a wood, perſecute them with thy tempests, and make them afraid with thy ſtorm.</hi> 6. <hi>Fill their faces with ſhame.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. <hi>16.</hi> &amp; <hi>17.</hi> Ver. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> 7. <hi>Let them be confounded and troubled for ever, yea, let them be put to ſhame and periſh; that men may know, that thou art the most High over all the earth,</hi> (and over all counſels, powers, and poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates therein.) Tell me now, whether in any like compaſſe of words, you find the like jealouſie, wrath, and indignation from God, againſt any ſin, as againſt this here of Sacrilege? I will not except Idolatry.</p>
               <p>And theſe are the Originals, from which our Chriſtian Benefactors have copied out their ſeveral Curſes upon the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaders of Church-Lands; holding it juſt to pray for a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of them from God, who ſeparate, and take that from God, which is his, and is given to the Church.</p>
               <p>I fear, ſome with a ſtrong breath, will ſeem to drive all this away, by ſaying, Theſe threats and curſes indeed we find in the Old Teſtament, where God had given the Jewes lawes, and commands againſt this ſin; but, in the New Teſtament, as you find not any Tithes or Lands appointed; ſo, neither have you any lawes or puniſhments herein, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to keep them untouched.</p>
               <p>But, to ſtop ſuch mouths, hear our Saviour,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 16.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Ye have Moſes and the Prophets, hear ye them:</hi> where Chriſt ſends us, though not from, yet in the Goſpel to the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and, as a Comment thereon, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Now all theſe things happened unto them,</hi> (as before you read) <hi>for enſample, and they are written for our admonition, upon whom the ends of the world are come.</hi> So, that not a tittle of what hath been alleged againſt Sacrilege in the Old Teſtament, but may, and ought rightly to ſerve for the inſtruction and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of all Sacrilegious perſons, who live now, and profeſſe the Goſpel. And juſtly, for, as I proved before, from
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:115963:42"/>
                  <hi>Deuteronomy, Leviticus, Proverbs,</hi> and the Prophet <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachi,</hi> this is a ſin againſt Gods Moral Law, both natural, and poſitive. And, yet we want not dehortation enough, and ſevere puniſhment enough of this ſin, in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: I ſhall cite but two Texts; and wonder not that I cite no more, but, rather wonder, that the Holy Ghoſt there had left ſo much; conſidering, 1. that he had been ſo plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and large againſt it in the Old Teſtament. 2. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that, whilſt the Apoſtles lived, they were ſo far from having Lands, or Tithes, or ſetled maintenance, that they had not houſes, nor holes to put their heads in, except they were in priſons; and therefore, then to write againſt taking away the Lands, and goods of the Church, when they had neither, would have been accounted but a labour in vain: and notwithſtanding all this, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> the one by his ſound Doctrine, the other by his miraculous power, have taught and admoniſhed every good Chriſtian enough, whereby to avoid, and beware of Sacrilege.</p>
               <p>I will begin with the Doctrinal part, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.22. which is ſo plainly ſet down, (as before I made appear) that all the beſt Divines doe, and cannot but confeſſe from that Text, that alienating the Church-Lands, is a ſin of an high na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and therefore utterly to be abhorred.<note place="margin">Acts <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> And, what judgment hath paſſed upon this ſin, is as plain in the ſtory and caſe of <hi>Ananias,</hi> who, for detaining but part of that which he had promiſed to God for the Church, was ſuddenly ſtruck dead: which viſible death, ſayes M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> on the place, was <hi>Symbolum,</hi> the fore-reckoning, or fore-ſhot of the death eternal; which, ſaith he, was juſt, 1. to puniſh <hi>Ananias</hi> for ſo hainous a ſin: 2. to admoniſh allo after him. For, had not Saint <hi>Peter</hi> thus ſeverely puniſht this ſin, many, ſaith M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Calvin,</hi> under colour of Religion, would have been forward to have robbed the Church.</p>
               <p>And, now for cloſe of all, will you be pleaſed to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the Sacrilege now intended, and begun, in ſelling the Biſhops Lands, with that of <hi>Ananias?</hi> Where, 1. he ſold onely the lands, which were his own; but here that is taken
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:115963:42"/>away, and ſold, that is Gods. 2. He had but promiſed thoſe lands to God, but here in theſe lands, God, and his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes and Servants, have for his uſe, been in real and actual poſſeſſion many hundreds of years. 3. He there kept back but a part; but here, all muſt be taken away, both root and branch. 4. There, probably, he might think to keep back a part, whereby to maintain himſelf, his wife, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily alive, in the great perſecution: but, here the rich and wealthy take them away, thereby to joyn land unto land, and Gods inheritance to their own poſſeſſions. 5. It may well be conceived, that, as this <hi>Ananias</hi> was but one pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man of no great note, ſo that he might be of no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary knowledge, and underſtanding; but more then probable, that he being a New Convert from Judaiſm, or Paganiſm, was but a novioe in the Law of God, or at leaſt of Chriſt: whereas they, who take and ſell theſe Lands, are many, ſelected, and choſen, as the wiſeſt, ableſt, moſt juſt in this great Kingdom; and then, how far this Sacrilege doth exceed that of <hi>Ananias,</hi> in reſpect of the perſons, the matter, the manner, and almoſt all circumſtances, judge you.</p>
               <p>And, yet I may adde one circumſtance more, which doth heighten this fin, as much, if not more then any other; for, in the late Covenant, you have ſworn to extirpate Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopacy, which is the main and leading cauſe in the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, wherefore the Lands of Biſhops muſt be ſold; and not onely have you ſworn this your ſelves, but, by threats, and forfeits, have urged, even the Biſhops themſelves to take the ſame: ſo, that they, who are to be ſpoiled and undone, are urged, contrary to Law, Juſtice, and Nature, to ſwear their own extirpation. O heavens! O earth! I had almoſt ſaid, O hell! Did you ever hear the like?</p>
               <p>In the Preface to the Covenant it is ſaid, that this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is made according to the commendable practice of this Kingdom, and the example of Gods people; and, I doubt not, but it hath been Preached, (as it hath been Printed) that this Covenant is warranted, as agreeable to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants in holy Writ, and in the beſt Reformed Churches:
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:115963:43"/>how truly this is ſpoken and printed, I refer to that which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Nye,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cov. with nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative. p. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> one of the Aſſembly, hath printed; where he ſaith, <hi>It is ſuch an Oath, the like hath not been in any age, or Oath we read of in ſacred, or humane Stories.</hi> And, I ſay, that when this ſhall be proved by the Word of God, by the example of Gods people, and the commendable pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of this Kingdom, that a few of the people, without their Head, did firſt covenant themſelves; and then by threats, fears, and puniſhments, did compel all, both head and tail, to extirpate the Religion long ſetled by Law, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the bloud of many holy Martyrs; againſt which, nothing is brought in proof, that it is repugnant to Gods Word:) and thereupon, to take and ſell away, what was lawfully given to God for the maintenance of his Servants in the Church; I ſay, when this ſhall be proved, I will take the Covenant; both which will be <hi>ad Graecas Calendas,</hi> that is, as we ſay, the morrow after Doomeſday, or never.</p>
               <p>I have proved, that alienating of theſe Lands, in Gods Law is Theft; and I have ſhewed Gods threats and judgments againſt this ſin; we have a proverb, what need a rich man be a Theef? (for few but ſuch caſt in their lots for Chriſts garment) and thereby to hazard the wrath of God, and their own fatal execution? The Philiſtims, a people out of the Covenant of God,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6.</note> yet for detaining, but a while, the Ark, wherein the Law was kept, were ſhamefully puniſhed in their hinder parts, and ſome with death; which cauſed the living to reſtore what was unjuſtly taken, with intereſt of much gold. And when <hi>Moab</hi> and <hi>Ammon</hi> had conſulted, covenanted, and voted, utterly to take away Gods inheritance; it ſo came to paſſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>83.</hi>
                  </note> that after all the Church flouriſhed and kept her own, when <hi>Moab</hi> and <hi>Ammon</hi> were utterly extinct, and laid in the duſt: which like conſideration, hath moved ſome, as wiſe, as pious, never to mingle their other lands wlth the Churches inheritance; and others, as pious, as wiſe, never in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to give aſſent to any Bils, for the Alienation of Church-Lands.</p>
               <p>It is conceived by many holy, and learned Divines, that
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:115963:43"/>the 74. Pſalm was penned, upon the robbing of the Temple at Jeruſalem, by <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes;</hi> which if ſo, then read and conſider the ſorrow, confeſſion, and death of that <hi>Antiochus:</hi> Now, ſaith he,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Macc.</hi> 6.12.</note> 
                  <hi>I remember the evils that I did at Jeruſalem, that I took away all the veſſels of gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that were therein: I perceive therefore, that for this cauſe, troubles are come upon me, and behold, I periſh through great grief.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is time you will ſay to conclude, and I pray, let it be with Prayer, and ſuch as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> uſed in his Comment on <hi>Acts</hi> 5. Lord grant, that, as, upon the ſudden fearful pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of <hi>Ananias</hi> his Sacrilege,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 5.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Fear came upon all the Church, and upon as many as heard theſe things,</hi> ſo the ſame, or the like fear, may ſtrike all our hearts, that ſo, (out of a true love, and due honor to God, and that we may eſcape the dreadful curſes and puniſhments, threatned and inflicted on this ſin) we may in time, while it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to day, repent us of this, and all other our ſins, and ſo obtain mercy, and eternal life in Chriſt Jeſus our only Lord, and Saviour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be wiſe now therefore, O ye Kings,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.10.</note> 
                  <hi>be inſtructed ye Judges of the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Serve the Lord with fear, and rejoyce with trembling.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Kiſſe the Son leſt he be angry, and ye periſh.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:115963:44"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>TItle Pag.</hi> [And what is given to God is holy, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 48.] <hi>add in the Margin p.</hi> 5. <hi>l.</hi> 19. Matth. 10.1, 40, 41, 42. Mark 9.41. John 13.20. <hi>p.</hi> 6. <hi>l.</hi> 17. <hi>dele</hi> &amp; Lev. 27.32. <hi>p.</hi> 9. <hi>l.</hi> 29. <hi>d.</hi> Ibid. <hi>p.</hi> 53. <hi>in mar. p.</hi> 17. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>for</hi> here. <hi>r.</hi> hear. <hi>p.</hi> 19. <hi>l.</hi> 14. Mat. 19.19. <hi>p.</hi> 32. <hi>l.</hi> 30. <hi>d.</hi> Exod. 23.2. <hi>r.</hi> Num. 16.38. <hi>p.</hi> 33. <hi>l.</hi> 33. Pro. <hi>for</hi> 25.20. <hi>r.</hi> 20.25. <hi>in mar. p.</hi> 34. <hi>l.</hi> 31. <hi>for</hi> Ball. Catoples. <hi>r.</hi> Bell. Staplet. <hi>in marg. p.</hi> 41. <hi>l.</hi> 11. <hi>for</hi> 3. <hi>r.</hi> 4. <hi>in mar. p.</hi> 42.12. <hi>r.</hi> Gal. 4.15. <hi>p.</hi> 43. <hi>l.</hi> 29. <hi>r.</hi> abaſed. <hi>p.</hi> 48. <hi>l. penul. r.</hi> 47. <hi>in mar. p.</hi> 52. <hi>l.</hi> 20. <hi>r.</hi> 25 Hen. 8. <hi>c.</hi> 20. <hi>in mar. p.</hi> 55. <hi>l.</hi> 25. <hi>for</hi> Covenant <hi>r.</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. <hi>p.</hi> 60. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>r.</hi> Chriſt and S. Peter. <hi>p.</hi> 61. <hi>l. penult. r.</hi> Rom. 3.8 <hi>in marg. p.</hi> 64. <hi>l.</hi> 33. <hi>r.</hi> 1 Sam. 22.18. <hi>p.</hi> 69. <hi>l.</hi> 33. <hi>r.</hi> Mat. 4.17. <hi>in mar. p.</hi> 75. <hi>l.</hi> 26. <hi>for</hi> 5. <hi>r.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 29. <hi>for</hi> 8. <hi>r.</hi> 7. <hi>l.</hi> 32. <hi>for</hi> 9. <hi>r.</hi> 8. <hi>l.</hi> 36. <hi>for</hi> 9. <hi>r.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 76. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>for.</hi> 11. <hi>r.</hi> 12. <hi>p.</hi> 80 <hi>for</hi> 1 Chro. 6 <hi>r.</hi> 1 Sam. 6. <hi>n mar.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115963:44"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
